<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3097211</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21673790</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-02456</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019860</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Regulation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject><subject>Gene Function</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Host-Pathogen Interaction</subject><subject>Parasitology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Nucleic Acids</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cellular Stress Responses</subject><subject>Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Parasitic Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Malaria</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The Puf-Family <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P09339,P70920,Q6NH63,Q8FTA8,Q8NQ98,Q4JVM4,Q937N8,Q9RTN7,P25516,Q2A1K3,O08451,A0QX20,O53166,Q9I3F5,Q1RKD5,Q92G90,Q4UK20,Q9ZCF4,Q68VV0,Q8ZP52,Q5HG69,P63433,P99148,Q6GH55,Q6G9K9,P63434,Q5HPJ0,Q8CPC2,Q59938,Q5SMF6,P36683,Q9ZL64,P56418,Q9I2V5,Q8ZRS8,P74582,P37032,P28890,Q85442,A4PBQ0,P13278,P31612,P82866,P56958">RNA-Binding Protein</z:uniprot> Puf2 Controls Sporozoite Conversion to Liver Stages in the Malaria Parasite </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Puf2 and <italic>Plasmodium</italic> Sporozoite Transformation</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>Katja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matuschewski</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silvie</surname><given-names>Olivier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">
<sup>¤</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology, Parasitology Unit, Berlin, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Gruner</surname><given-names>Anne Charlotte</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Agency for Science, Technology and Research (A*STAR), Singapore</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>olivier.silvie@inserm.fr</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Müller K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Matuschewski OS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Müller OS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Müller K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Matuschewski OS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Matuschewski OS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff"><label>¤</label><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Current address: INSERM UMR_S 945 "Immunity and infection", Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Pitié-<z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q9R226">Salp</z:uniprot>ê<z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="12" ids="P95871,P96086,Q97A95">tri</z:uniprot>ère, Faculté de Médecine et Université Pierre et Marie Curie, Paris, France </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ecorrected"><day>24
</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e19860</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>2</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Müller et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Malaria is a vector-borne infectious disease caused by unicellular, obligate intracellular parasites of the genus Plasmodium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>During host switch the malaria parasite employs specialized latent stages that colonize the new host environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Previous work has established that gametocytes, sexually differentiated stages that are taken up by the mosquito vector, control expression of genes required for mosquito colonization by translational repression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Sexual parasite development is controlled by a DEAD-box RNA helicase of the <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q9WTM2,Q5ZKB9,P26196,Q5RFQ5">DDX6</z:uniprot> family, termed DOZI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Latency of sporozoites, the transmission stage injected during an infectious blood meal, is controlled by the <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q9FE78">eIF2alpha</z:uniprot> kinase IK2, a general inhibitor of protein synthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Whether <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P09339,P70920,Q6NH63,Q8FTA8,Q8NQ98,Q4JVM4,Q937N8,Q9RTN7,P25516,Q2A1K3,O08451,A0QX20,O53166,Q9I3F5,Q1RKD5,Q92G90,Q4UK20,Q9ZCF4,Q68VV0,Q8ZP52,Q5HG69,P63433,P99148,Q6GH55,Q6G9K9,P63434,Q5HPJ0,Q8CPC2,Q59938,Q5SMF6,P36683,Q9ZL64,P56418,Q9I2V5,Q8ZRS8,P74582,P37032,P28890,Q85442,A4PBQ0,P13278,P31612,P82866,P56958">RNA-binding proteins</z:uniprot> participate in translational regulation in sporozoites remains to be studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Here, we investigated the roles of two <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P09339,P70920,Q6NH63,Q8FTA8,Q8NQ98,Q4JVM4,Q937N8,Q9RTN7,P25516,Q2A1K3,O08451,A0QX20,O53166,Q9I3F5,Q1RKD5,Q92G90,Q4UK20,Q9ZCF4,Q68VV0,Q8ZP52,Q5HG69,P63433,P99148,Q6GH55,Q6G9K9,P63434,Q5HPJ0,Q8CPC2,Q59938,Q5SMF6,P36683,Q9ZL64,P56418,Q9I2V5,Q8ZRS8,P74582,P37032,P28890,Q85442,A4PBQ0,P13278,P31612,P82866,P56958">RNA-binding proteins</z:uniprot> of the Puf-family, Plasmodium Puf1 and Puf2, during sporozoite stage conversion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Our data reveal that, in the rodent malaria parasite P. berghei, Puf2 participates in the regulation of IK2 and inhibits premature sporozoite transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Inside mosquito salivary glands puf2(-) sporozoites transform over time to round forms resembling early intra-hepatic stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>As a result, mutant parasites display strong defects in initiating a malaria infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In contrast, Puf1 is dispensable in vivo throughout the entire Plasmodium life cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Our findings support the notion of a central role for Puf2 in parasite latency during switch between the insect and mammalian hosts. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Plasmodium parasites, the causative agents of malaria, are transmitted by female Anopheles mosquitoes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>During the probing phase prior to the blood meal, sporozoites are injected into the skin of the mammalian host [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The motile sporozoites actively migrate in the skin, enter the peripheral blood circulation, and then rapidly reach the liver. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Sporozoites invade hepatocytes by forming a parasitophorous vacuole (PV) [2], where they transform into replicative exo-erythrocytic forms (EEFs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>After intense multiplication during 2–6 days, depending on the Plasmodium species, mature EEFs release thousands of merozoites, which invade erythrocytes and initiate the pathogenic blood stage cycle [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Plasmodium sporozoites are formed inside oocysts in the mosquito midgut, but become fully infective only after colonization of the insect salivary glands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>This maturation process is associated with the up-regulation of a specific subset of genes, referred to as Up-regulated in Infective Sporozoites (UIS) genes [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Regulation of gene expression in Plasmodium remains poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Genome sequencing data initially revealed a paucity of specific transcription factors in Plasmodium [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Recently however, a family of genes related to the plant Apetala-2 (<z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="A1A4R9,P05549,P34056,P58197,Q9N0N3">AP2</z:uniprot>) transcription factors has been identified in Plasmodium and related apicomplexan parasites [6], [7], and proposed to play a central role during life cycle progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Molecular genetic studies have demonstrated vital roles of two stage-specific <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="A1A4R9,P05549,P34056,P58197,Q9N0N3">AP2</z:uniprot> factors in Plasmodium berghei, a rodent malaria parasite widely used as a model [8], [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>One of these factors, the <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="A1A4R9,P05549,P34056,P58197,Q9N0N3">AP2</z:uniprot>-Sp transcription factor, is required during sporozoite differentiation and binds to a specific DNA sequence found in the promoter region of many genes expressed in sporozoites, including, but not restricted to, UIS genes [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, genes containing <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="A1A4R9,P05549,P34056,P58197,Q9N0N3">AP2</z:uniprot>-Sp binding sites are associated with a wide range of biological processes, such as sporozoite formation, host cell invasion or liver stage development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>This observation strongly suggests that additional mechanisms participate in the fine-tuning of gene expression during sporozoite development and stage conversion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Another factor, called SLARP or <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P28324,P41158,Q9HD43,E9Q0N2,P98185">SAP1</z:uniprot>, controls the expression of a subset of genes in sporozoites, and plays a critical role during intrahepatic development of the parasite [10], [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>It is still unclear whether SLARP/<z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P28324,P41158,Q9HD43,E9Q0N2,P98185">SAP1</z:uniprot> acts on a transcriptional or a post-transcriptional level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The cellular localization of SLARP/<z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P28324,P41158,Q9HD43,E9Q0N2,P98185">SAP1</z:uniprot> remains controversial [10], [11], and the absence of any domain known to bind nucleic acids suggests an indirect role. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>More recently, Zhang and colleagues reported that the protein kinase IK2, initially termed UIS1 [4], controls global gene expression in sporozoites at a post-transcriptional level [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>IK2 phosphorylates the translation initiation factor <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q9FE78">eIF2alpha</z:uniprot> and down-regulates protein synthesis [12], [13]. P. berghei lacking UIS1/IK2 display a partial loss of infectivity associated with premature transformation of sporozoites in the mosquito salivary glands [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The contribution of RNA-binding prxoteins in translational regulation has not been studied in sporozoites yet, but has been well characterized in Plasmodium sexual stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>In female gametocytes, many transcripts encoding ookinete proteins are translationally repressed by a DEAD-box RNA helicase called DOZI, which binds to the 3′ untranslated region (UTR) of target mRNAs such as <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="5" ids="Q39604">P28</z:uniprot> and blocks their translation until occurrence of gamete fertilization and differentiation into a zygote and ookinete [14], [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Whether DOZI plays a role in sporozoites is not known, but other <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P09339,P70920,Q6NH63,Q8FTA8,Q8NQ98,Q4JVM4,Q937N8,Q9RTN7,P25516,Q2A1K3,O08451,A0QX20,O53166,Q9I3F5,Q1RKD5,Q92G90,Q4UK20,Q9ZCF4,Q68VV0,Q8ZP52,Q5HG69,P63433,P99148,Q6GH55,Q6G9K9,P63434,Q5HPJ0,Q8CPC2,Q59938,Q5SMF6,P36683,Q9ZL64,P56418,Q9I2V5,Q8ZRS8,P74582,P37032,P28890,Q85442,A4PBQ0,P13278,P31612,P82866,P56958">RNA-binding proteins</z:uniprot> may participate in translational regulation in sporozoites, including members of the Puf-family. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Puf proteins are evolutionary conserved in eukaryotes and are characterized by the presence of a RNA-binding Puf domain, named after the Drosophila melanogaster protein Pumilio and the Caenorhabditis elegans protein <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q8I8U6,P34691,Q8I8W7">fem-3</z:uniprot> binding factor (FBF), and consisting of eight imperfect repeats of 36 amino acids (PFAM: PF00806) [16], [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Puf proteins typically bind to the 3′ UTR of target mRNAs and repress their translation or induce their degradation (reviewed in [18] and [19]). Plasmodium parasites possess two genes encoding proteins with Puf domains, Puf1 and Puf2 [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In P. falciparum, both Puf1 (PFE0935c) and Puf2 (PFD0825c) are differentially expressed in gametocytes [20], [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Targeted gene disruption in P. falciparum recently revealed a role of PfPuf2 in repressing gametocytogenesis and male gametocyte differentiation in the human malaria parasite [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Whether the Puf2 protein plays additional, perhaps vital, roles in subsequent life cycle stages remains to be shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, microarray data indicate that Puf2 is most highly expressed in P. falciparum sporozoites [23], and in P. berghei, expression of both Puf1 (PBANKA_123350) and Puf2 (PBANKA_071920) has been reported in sporozoites, where Puf1 was initially identified as UIS9 [4], [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used a reverse genetic approach to investigate the roles of Puf1 and Puf2 in P. berghei, with the aim to identify potential mRNA binding proteins that play critical roles in sporozoite stage conversion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Targeted gene deletion of P. berghei Puf1 and Puf2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>We first assessed the expression of Puf1 and Puf2 during P. berghei development in the insect vector, in comparison to DOZI and UIS1/IK2, using quantitative RT-PCR ( Figure 1  ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Similarly to UIS1/IK2 [12], we found that Puf1 and Puf2 are upregulated in P. berghei salivary gland sporozoites ( Figure 1  ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>This was expected for Puf1, which was initially described as UIS9 [4], [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, Puf1 was also upregulated in gametocytes and ookinetes, similarly to IK2 and DOZI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>In good agreement with published microarray data [24], only low levels of DOZI mRNA were detected in P. berghei sporozoites ( Figure 1 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>In contrast to Puf1 and Puf2, DOZI steady state mRNA levels were down-regulated in infectious salivary gland-associated sporozoites resulting in ∼100 fold lower levels in the latent transmission stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Together, the expression profiling indicated that both Puf members could play a role in sporozoite stage conversion, as has been described previously for the <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q9FE78">eIF2alpha</z:uniprot> kinase UIS1/IK2 [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019860-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019860.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Puf1 and Puf2 are upregulated in P. berghei sporozoites. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Shown is an expression profiling of selected transcripts of RNA regulatory proteins, the <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q9WTM2,Q5ZKB9,P26196,Q5RFQ5">DDX6</z:uniprot>-family DEAD-box helicase DOZI [15], the Puf proteins Puf1 and Puf2 [20], and of the <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q9FE78">eIF2alpha</z:uniprot> kinase UIS1/IK2 that controls sporozoite latency [12]. P. berghei purified gametocytes, ookinetes, oocysts and salivary gland sporozoites were analyzed by RT-qPCR using primers specific for DOZI, UIS1/IK2, Puf1 and Puf2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Expression data from two independent experiments are shown and were normalized to the level of <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="2" ids="P42212">GFP</z:uniprot> transcripts, which are expressed under the control of the <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P29521,P0CT31,P34824,P06805,P17506,P34823,P0CT32,Q40034,P14864,P14865,P28295,P84321,Q9YAV0,P40911,P84322,P19039,O29325,P02993,P41752,Q9Y713,Q00251,P41745,P54959,P29520,P53013,A8MAJ1,A0RUM4,Q96WZ1,P0CN31,P0CN30,P90519,Q92005,P41203,Q07051,Q8SS29,P31018,P14963,Q08046,P16018,B0R8C3,Q9HM89,Q18EY5,P84319,P84317,P84320,P84318,P84315,P84316,P51554,A2BN41,P34825,A8ABM5,Q41803,O49169,A6UV43,Q8TRC4,Q0W8G2,A7I656,Q464Z4,Q12WT3,Q2FRI3,Q57770,Q8TYP6,A2STF0,A4FWE9,A9A9U3,A6VGV6,Q8PUR8,A3CTG3,Q6LXI1,B8GIQ3,A5ULM5,A4YCR6,Q2NEL1,O27132,A0B7D6,P07810,A6UQ14,P81266,Q74MI6,Q3IUD8,Q01372,P27592,Q9YIC0,O64937,Q41011,A5DPE3,Q6L202,Q00080,Q01520,Q01765,P85915,P32186,Q9V0V7,O93729,A4WKK8,A3MV69,Q8U152,O59153,A1RRJ3,P26751,Q8LPC4,P27634,P35021,O42820,Q9HDF6,P17786,Q09069,P25698,Q26487,A3DMQ1,P25166,P17196,Q976B1,Q04634,P19486,P17197,C5A5P4,Q5JFZ4,B6YVG2,A1RXW9,C6A4R7,Q979T1,P43643,P86933,O24534,Q03033,O59949,P02994">EF1alpha</z:uniprot> promoter [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019860.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>In order to investigate the functional importance of Puf1/UIS9 and Puf2 in P. berghei, we generated loss-of-function mutants ( Figure 2 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>We used a replacement strategy to disrupt the endogenous Puf1 ( Figure 2A ) or Puf2 ( Figure 2B ) gene copy by double crossover homologous recombination [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Targeting constructs containing 5′ and 3′ fragments of either Puf1 or Puf2 flanking a pyrimethamine-resistance cassette were used to transfect P. berghei parasites that constitutively express <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="2" ids="P42212">GFP</z:uniprot> (ANKA cl507) [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Recombinant parasites were selected with pyrimethamine in the mouse drinking water, and cloned by limiting dilutions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>For both genes we were successful in generating clonal knockout parasite populations, as demonstrated by PCR and Southern blot analysis of genomic DNA ( Figures 2C–F ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>For Puf2 we also generated a second independent knockout clone, which was phenotypically identical to the first puf2(-) clonal parasite line (unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>This indicates that Puf1 and Puf2 do not play any vital role during P. berghei erythrocytic stages, in good agreement with successful generation of Pfpuf2(-) parasites [22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019860-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019860.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Targeted gene deletion of Puf1/UIS9 and Puf2 in P. berghei. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>(A–B) Replacement strategy to generate the puf1(-) and puf2(-) parasites. P. berghei PUF1 gene (A) consists of five exons encoding an 1183 amino-acid protein (PBANKA_123350), whereas <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q12221">PUF2</z:uniprot> (B) consists of four exons encoding a 477 amino-acid protein (PBANKA_071920). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The PUF domains are shown in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>For each gene, the wild-type (WT) genomic locus was targeted with a replacement plasmid containing 5′ and 3′ regions of PUF1 or <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q12221">PUF2</z:uniprot> and a positive selectable marker, Toxoplasma gondii dhfr/ts or human <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="4" ids="P28019,P00376,P00378,Q07801,Q9U8B8,P00374,P04753,P00377,P09503,P27421,P22573,Q5HFZ7,P0A016,P99079,Q6GGY1,Q6G9D5,P0A017,Q8NWQ9,P0C0P0,Q5HPB1,P0C0P1,Q60034,A8AGY5,A7ZM66,P0AFS4,A8A0E8,A1ABF1,Q0THM2,Q8FHB1,B1IQY4,P0AFS3,B1LET0,Q1RBJ2,A4W9Z4,A6T8N3,Q320W2,Q32G72,Q0T4H1,Q83RC9,Q3Z1V9">DHFR</z:uniprot>, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Upon a double crossover event, the PUF1 or <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q12221">PUF2</z:uniprot> gene is replaced by the selectable marker. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Replacement- and wild type- specific test primer combinations and expected PCR fragments (WT, 5′ integration and 3′ integration) are indicated by arrows and lines, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Restriction sites, Southern probes and expected restriction fragments are also shown. S, SpeI; X, XhoI; A, AfeI; E, EcoRV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>(C) Puf1 replacement-specific PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Confirmation of the predicted gene targeting is achieved by specific primer combinations (5′ and 3′ integration), which can only amplify a signal from the recombinant locus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>A wild type-specific PCR reaction confirms the absence of residual wild-type parasites in the clonal puf1(-) population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>(D) Southern blot analysis of genomic DNA isolated from WT, puf1(-) and puf2(-) parasites, using digoxigenin-labelled probes specific for Puf1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>After digest with SpeI and XhoI, the Puf1 probe hybridizes to a 8.3 or a 6.9 kb fragment in WT and puf1(-) parasites, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>(E) Puf2 replacement-specific PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Confirmation of the predicted gene targeting is achieved by specific primer combinations (5′ and 3′ integration), which can only amplify a signal from the recombinant locus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>A wild type-specific PCR reaction confirms the absence of residual wild-type parasites in the clonal puf2(-) population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>(F) Southern blot analysis of genomic DNA isolated from WT, puf1(-) and puf2(-) parasites, using digoxigenin-labelled probes specific for Puf2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>After digest with AfeI and EcoRV, the Puf2 probe hybridizes to a 8.4 kb fragment in WT and a 4.0 kb fragment in puf2(-) parasites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019860.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>puf1(-) and puf2(-) parasites produce gametocytes that develop to sporozoites in mosquitoes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>puf1(-) and puf2(-) parasites were indistinguishable from WT parasites in development and growth of asexual blood stages and produced gametocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Because PfPuf2 has been shown to control gametocytogenesis in P. falciparum [22], we analyzed in more detail the sexual development of P. berghei puf2(-) parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>After injection of 107 infected erythrocytes intravenously into groups of five C57BL/6 mice, parasitemia at day 4 were similar in mice infected with WT or puf2(-) ( Figure 3A ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>However, the proportion of gametocytes among all parasite stages was significantly higher in puf2(-) than in WT parasites ( Figure 3B ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>We then examined the ability of mature male gametocytes to exflagellate in puf2(-) parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The number of exflagellation centers in mouse blood was significantly higher for puf2(-) parasites than for WT parasites ( Figure 3C ), suggesting that male gametocytes contribute to the increased gametocytogenesis in Pbpuf2(-) parasites, in full support of the data reported for P. falciparum Puf2-deficient parasites [22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019860-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019860.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Gametocytogenesis is increased in puf2(-) parasites. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Groups of C57BL/6 mice (n = 5) were injected intravenously with 107 WT or puf2(-) infected erythrocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Blood was collected from the mice 4 days later to determine the parasitemia (A), the proportion of gametocytes among parasites (B), and the number of exflagellation centers per µl of blood (C). Results are expressed as mean +/− SEM. **, p&lt;0.01 (Mann-Whitney test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019860.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>After transmission to Anopheles stephensi mosquitoes, both puf1(-) and puf2(-) parasite lines produced oocysts and high numbers of sporozoites ( Table 1 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The number of puf2(-) oocysts was significantly higher than for WT, consistent with the higher gametocyte rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, we found lower numbers of oocysts and salivary gland sporozoites in puf1(-)-infected mosquitoes, as compared to WT parasites ( Table 1 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Although the differences were not statistically significant, we cannot exclude an effect of puf1 depletion on oocyst development and sporogony. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0019860-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019860.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Loss of infectivity of puf2(-) sporozoites in C57BL/6 mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0019860-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0019860.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Parasites </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Number of oocysts/mosquitoa (mean ± SD) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Number of salivary gland sporozoites/mosquitoa (mean ± SD) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Route of injectionb </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Number of infected/Number of injected </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Prepatency period (days)c </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>WT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>182 (± 164) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>31,600 (± 18,600) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>bites (d 21) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>3/3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>i.v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>(d 18) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>2/2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>i.v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>(d 21) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>6/6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>3.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>i.v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>(d 25) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>4/4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>puf1(-) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>137 (± 100) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>11,400 (± 4,700) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>bites (d 17) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>3/3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>i.v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>(d 21) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>6/6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>3.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>puf2(-) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>320 (± 234)d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>25,000 (± 18,800) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>bites (d 21) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>3/4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>(5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>i.v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>(d 18) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>2/4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>(5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>i.v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>(d 25) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>0/4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>NA </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The number of midgut oocysts and salivary gland sporozoites was determined at d10–14 and d18–25, respectively, after the infectious blood meal, from at least three independent feeding experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>b</label><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>C57BL/6 mice were exposed to the bites of 10 infected mosquitoes or injected intravenously (i.v.) with 1,000 sporozoites, 18–25 days after mosquito infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>c</label><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The prepatent period is defined as the number of days after sporozoite inoculation until detection of infected erythrocytes by microscopic blood smear examination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Brackets indicate that not all animals became infected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>NA, not applicable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>d</label><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>p&lt;0.05 in comparison to WT, as determined by Kruskal-Wallis followed by Dunn's test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Liver infection is impaired in Puf2-deficient parasites </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>We then analysed the infectivity of puf1(-) and puf2(-) sporozoites to susceptible mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>C57BL/6 mice were injected intravenously with 1,000 WT, puf1(-) or puf2(-) P. berghei sporozoites, or exposed to the bites of 10 infected mosquitoes, the natural transmission route ( Table 1 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Emergence of erythrocytic stages, resulting from complete liver stage development, was monitored by microscopic examination of daily blood smears. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>With both inoculation routes, all mice injected with puf1(-) sporozoites developed a parasitemia, with no delay as compared to WT parasites ( Table 1 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In contrast, only a fraction of the mice injected with puf2(-) sporozoites developed a parasitemia, with a two-day delay as compared to WT, indicative of at least 100-fold reduction of infectivity ( Table 1 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Moreover, puf2(-) sporozoites isolated late after mosquito infection (at day 25) were not capable of inducing a blood stage infection in mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>We next injected C57BL/6 mice intravenously with WT, puf1(-) or puf2(-) sporozoites isolated on day 18 from mosquito salivary glands. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Forty-two hours after infection, livers were removed and the parasite loads were quantified by RT-qPCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>As shown in  Figure 4 , the puf2(-) liver loads were extremely reduced (∼500 fold) as compared to WT, confirming that infectivity of puf2(-) sporozoites to C57BL/6 mice is severely impaired. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The reduction of parasite liver loads as measured by RT-qPCR is consistent with the delay or absence of parasitemia in mice injected with puf2(-) sporozoites ( Table 1 ), therefore we assume that the absence of Puf2 did not interfere with 18S rRNA quantification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we also observed a significant, although less pronounced (∼4 fold), reduction of puf1(-) parasite liver loads ( Figure 4 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Our findings demonstrate that PbPuf2 plays an important in vivo role only in the pre-erythrocytic phase of the Plasmodium life cycle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>In contrast, Puf1/UIS9 appears to be dispensable for parasite life cycle progression, at least under the conditions tested. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019860-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019860.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Liver infection is severely impaired in puf2(-) parasites. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Parasite loads were determined by RT-qPCR analysis of mouse livers (n = 4 or 5 per group) harvested 42 hours after intravenous injection of 10,000 WT, puf1(-) or puf2(-) sporozoites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Results are expressed as the relative expression of Pb18S normalized to mouse <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="1" ids="P09124,P53429,O34425,P25858,Q0J8A4,Q7FAH2,Q6K5G8,P25861,P50321,Q01558,P26518,P26519,P26520,P26521,P10097,O96423,Q27890,P22512,P22513,P50322,Q9YFS9,Q9HFX1,P55071,O67161,O28542,Q757I2,Q12552,Q9HGY7,P24750,P34783,P15115,Q59199,P23722,Q00640,Q00301,P46795,P46796,P10096,P48812,P57384,Q07234,Q89AK1,Q92211,Q28259,P70685,P00356,Q9PJN6,Q9Z7T0,B0B879,P0CE13,P24748,Q00584,O52631,Q59309,P29497,Q1DTF9,P28844,Q8J1H3,P35143,O57479,P54117,Q01651,Q05025,P17244,P0CN75,P0CN74,P19089,Q9Y796,Q5XJ10,Q6BMK0,Q94469,Q01597,Q27652,P0A9B3,P20445,B7LQ20,P0C8Z1,Q9N2D5,P00362,Q4U3L0,P44304,Q5V061,B0R2M2,Q9HSS7,Q48335,Q9ZKT0,P55971,P00357,P04406,P87197,A2BLC6,P80534,Q59800,P24163,P24164,O32755,P55070,P52987,Q9UR38,Q92243,Q9N655,O57672,P51640,A6UUN9,A7IB57,P19314,Q12XM4,P10618,P19315,Q2FNA2,Q58546,P58839,A4FZL2,A9A6M9,A6VIW4,Q8PTD3,A3CYG8,Q6M0E6,A5ULT9,A4YHA5,Q2NEN0,O27090,A6URW1,P53430,P16858,A3FKF7,P94915,P64179,A0A0H3MAB5,P47543,P46713,P75358,A0QWW2,P9WN82,P9WN83,P83601,Q3IUT3,P54118,O59841,Q8TFJ2,O42259,O01360,P56649,Q8X1X3,Q5R2J2,Q01982,Q9P8C0,O13507,P26988,Q92263,Q6L125,P00355,Q9UW96,P32637,Q5RAB4,P27726,P24751,Q9V1P1,Q8ZWK7,A4WIW2,A3MTU1,P61879,O59494,A1RV79,B1YD06,P61880,P46406,P52694,P04797,Q8NK47,P29272,P39460,P0A1P1,P0A1P0,P32638,P20287,Q96US8,P24166,P24753,Q28554,I2BA89,P0DJO7,P0A9B5,Q8WZN0,Q4KYY3,P0A038,Q9Z518,Q59906,P0C0G7,P0DB18,Q5XDW3,P68777,P0DB19,P0C0G6,Q4J940,C3N6F0,C4KHW5,C3MQN0,C3MWN0,C3NGT6,C3NEV8,Q971K2,Q9HJ69,P00361,Q5JHB5,P17721,B6YUU0,C6A312,Q97BJ8,O83816,P09317,Q9UVC0,P51009,P51469,Q6CCU7,P08439,P09316">GAPDH</z:uniprot>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The means +/− SEM are indicated by lines **, p&lt;0.01 (Mann-Whitney test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019860.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>We also determined the In vitro infectivity of puf1(-) and puf2(-) sporozoites isolated on day 22 from mosquito salivary glands, in cultured HepG2 hepatoma cells ( Figure 5 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Both puf1(-) and puf2(-) sporozoites entered hepatoma cells as efficiently as WT, as evidenced by similar numbers of infected cells at early time points (4–6 hours) ( Figure 5A ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>While the number of EEFs at later time points (24–48 hours) was similar in WT- and puf1(-)-infected cultures ( Figure 5A ), it was reduced in the case of puf2(-) parasites ( Figure 5B ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Whereas early after infection a vast majority (81% ±3%; n = 122) of intracellular WT sporozoites expressed UIS4, a transmembrane protein that localizes to the membrane of the PV [27], only half of puf2(-) parasites were stained with UIS4 antibodies (53% ±9%; n = 127). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>This indicates that a substantial fraction of puf2(-) sporozoites failed to form and/or remodel the PV in vitro, which probably explains the reduced EEF numbers quantified at later time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>In addition, we cannot exclude a moderate impairment during liver stage development in puf2(-) parasites, as suggested by the reduction of EEF numbers observed between 24 and 48 hours post-infection in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, most puf2(-) sporozoites that formed a PV and expressed UIS4 were capable of developing into EEFs like WT and puf1(-) parasites ( Figure 5C ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our data indicate that Puf2 plays a critical role during transmission of P. berghei sporozoites to the mammalian host, but is not required for liver stage development per se. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019860-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019860.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>puf2(-) sporozoites are infective in vitro. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>(A) HepG2 cells were infected with WT or puf1(-) sporozoites and the numbers of infected cells were determined at 6, 24 and 48 h post-infection (p.i.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Results are expressed as the mean number of infected cells in triplicate wells +/− SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>(B) HepG2 cells were infected with WT or puf2(-) sporozoites and the numbers of infected cells were determined at 4, 24 and 48 h post-infection (p.i.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Results are expressed as the mean number of infected cells in triplicate wells +/− SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>(C) Confocal microscopy analysis of HepG2 cells cultured for 5 and 24 hours post-infection (p.i.) with WT, puf1(-) or puf2(-) sporozoites, using antibodies against UIS4 (red), <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="28" ids="O33672,O33666,O33690,O33668,O33675,O33689,Q29455,Q9H3Z4,P60904,P60905,P56101,O42196">CSP</z:uniprot> (5 h p.i., green) or <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="2" ids="A1TLH9,Q6F6N3,B7H317,B7IBK5,B2HZZ7,A3M8W9,B0V5U4,A0LWS7,C1F2D2,P81875,A5FZ19,B9MDJ7,B7J7X9,B5ENA3,P29133,A1WAR6,A3N3K0,B3H2X7,B0BTI7,A6VNB1,A0KMI6,A4SQ25,P71331,P50019,B9JZ87,B2UKV6,Q0VST6,B5FA11,A6TSM0,B4S0U1,B3ERN8,Q5PAB8,P86175,B7GKC8,O52960,O67118,O86103,A8EWT6,Q5P1H5,A0K1L3,A8IPT1,B6YRF7,A1K4C5,C3P8M0,C3L5R7,A0RIT3,Q81LS2,B7JN39,Q730M1,B7IYG7,C1ESK8,B7HCU0,B7HPL3,A7GT08,B9IY81,Q818E9,Q634M7,Q5LG30,Q64X01,Q9KD72,Q6HDK7,Q65H54,P05646,A9VHU1,A8FFD2,Q5WHG1,P17820,Q89YW6,A6L2X7,A7Z6W1,A1UUC3,Q6G554,Q6G1F9,A9ILH7,Q1LST3,Q6MNF8,B2IBR4,C5C3P2,B8DT62,A1A3P5,B3DNP9,Q8G6W1,B7GT47,Q7VQL4,Q493S7,Q2KWA2,Q0SMZ0,Q661A3,Q7WGI4,P0C922,B7J282,B5RM75,B2S0M0,Q7W519,A9IGC3,Q7VVY2,B5RPM1,P94317,C0ZB48,Q9LCQ5,Q57AD7,Q8YE76,Q05981,Q8FXX2,B8D8V4,O32464,Q8K9Y8,B8D758,P59565,B1YTK0,Q1BYX3,B1JW19,P42373,A0K4S8,B4EDZ2,Q0BI18,Q39JC8,A9AGB8,A3MN99,A2S565,Q62HD5,A1V0U6,A3NYX7,Q3JP10,A3ND68,O68191,Q2SYZ4,A4JBS1,B9MJZ1,Q8RB68,A4XKA4,A7ZEB5,A7GXU4,A0RPW7,A7I2D4,A8FLH2,A7H484,O69298,Q5HV33,B9KCH0,Q3AF08,Q05FS8,B0T138,P20442,B3PF33,A0RZ01,Q11KJ6,Q8GH79,Q3APD2,Q824B2,Q253K1,B3EHR1,P56836,B3QMB2,B3EKT9,A1BET8,A4SFB1,P27542,B0B7W6,B3QZ38,Q3KLV7,B0BC31,Q8KEP3,P17821,Q1QSX0,Q7NXI3,A8ALU3,A5CM86,B0RBI1,P30721,A7FXL5,C3L3G7,A6LRN4,B2V2I5,B2TLZ7,A5I640,C1FVU0,B1ILM3,A7GHH6,B1KZN7,Q182E8,B9E041,A5N6M2,A0Q1R4,Q0TNS7,P81341,P26823,Q0SRE3,Q892R0,C3PJM6,Q6NEY9,Q8FM78,A4QHJ0,Q8NLY6,Q4JXX6,C4LGV8,B1VHX4,B6J7U7,B6IZJ0,A9KG88,A9N8H2,O87712,A7MIK5,O33522,Q0K757,Q46XI7,B3R6G7,P0CY98,P0CY99,Q9TLT1,Q85FW4,Q37106,Q11QH3,Q47HK2,Q3Z6P1,A5FPU4,Q3ZYV1,C1CZH9,Q1IWL4,P94695,Q9RY23,P83709,A9BNG5,C6BSF2,Q313S2,C0QGP6,B8FGS3,B1I699,B8J402,B8FUN4,C4XQ63,A8ZRW3,Q6AMQ3,A4J7F3,Q72DW8,B8DRD6,A1VFG6,P30722,A5EYG3,B5YAR3,B8DYH6,A7ZHA4,P0A6Z0,A7ZVV7,A1A766,Q0TLX5,P0A6Y9,B1IRG0,P0A6Y8,Q1RGI8,C5B7L7,Q3YRR6,Q5FFM4,Q5HAY1,B2KAX0,Q4G366,A4W6D5,Q835R7,B2VGR9,Q05647,C4Z1J4,B1YKS9,C4L425,B0S1F8,A5FGL1,A6GXZ1,Q0RBC4,B0TYF2,Q14GW9,A7NCM9,Q2A328,B2SGV8,A0Q7F0,Q0BLK4,Q5NFG7,P48205,A4IX28,Q8RH05,B5EC42,B9M357,Q5KWZ7,B3E7W9,Q39PT7,Q45551,Q74H59,C6E643,C5D4U1,A4IR31,A5GDC8,Q7NDH1,A9HEA3,Q5FSL5,Q0BW82,A0M353,Q6B8V2,P29215,P48209,Q4QJW4,A5UBQ1,A5UF68,P43736,B8F7S6,Q0I3V2,Q2SMM8,A1WX31,B9LUC7,Q01100,Q9HHB9,B8CXL1,B0R3H4,Q9HRY2,Q18GZ4,C4K3I6,Q17VY4,Q7VIE3,B0TAD7,B6JPL0,B5Z9P0,Q1CV46,Q9ZMW4,B2URT8,P55994,A4G8D2,B0UWR4,A3DF25,Q31HA7,Q0BWZ9,Q5QXL1,A6T226,Q28VY3,A6WFV7,B5Y242,A6T4F4,B2GGP0,Q1IT15,Q84BU4,Q03QU1,B3WEQ7,Q1G9R2,Q049W6,B2GBQ5,Q044A9,A8YVQ3,Q74IT6,P0A3J0,P0A3J1,Q02ZQ7,Q038N3,A9KKU0,Q88VM0,A5VJE7,B2G6W3,Q1WUE8,O87777,Q8KML6,Q38W93,C1DD88,Q1MPW1,Q5X3M7,A5IDK8,Q5ZTY3,Q5WV15,O32482,Q6AC76,B0SHT1,Q04VC8,Q04Y47,B0SRF1,B1Y786,P61442,P61443,B1MZG6,Q03WI2,Q92BN8,G2K046,C1KVC0,Q71ZJ7,B8DE38,P0DJM2,A0AIS4,B1HUD1,O69268,B9E6X1,A0L4Z2,Q2VYT1,O52064,Q65U55,A1U614,Q0AKB1,A6W2D2,Q9ZIV1,Q6F149,Q8TQR2,Q0W874,Q465Y6,Q12WE6,B7KSZ4,Q607A5,A9W6R7,Q1H3B8,B3DZP7,P0CW13,P0CW12,B8IHL3,B1ZGR1,A2SIR4,B1LZ51,B0UR84,B8EIP9,Q9ZFC6,Q9UXR0,O27351,A0B747,Q2RKX4,A0QLZ6,B1MIX5,A5IXT5,P80462,P0A5C0,A1KFH2,C1AK26,Q2SSB0,Q7NAU6,P47547,A4T112,Q49539,Q4A8U5,Q4AAR4,Q9ZEJ0,B8ZTB7,P19993,B2HPS1,Q6KIH7,Q6MT06,Q00488,Q8EUH7,P75344,Q98QY7,A0QQC8,Q4A658,A3PTN4,A1UA31,P80692,Q1BEV1,A5TZ77,P9WMJ8,P9WMJ9,A0PLQ1,A1T2S3,P95334,Q3IUI0,B9L8Z0,Q5F6W5,A9M296,Q9JVQ9,Q9K0N4,A1KSG3,O85282,Q2GF34,Q0AIY1,O06430,Q1QRU1,A9A135,Q2Y6U0,Q3J7D8,A6Q421,Q3SW76,Q5YNI0,A1SPX5,Q2G6N0,Q8EPW4,Q04EE1,B6JCI3,Q6YPM1,A6LDG8,A1B4E9,A7HZ39,B2JGE2,B2SXC6,Q9KWS7,Q6MB26,Q145F1,P57870,Q6D0B7,C6DF10,Q03FR7,Q3A8C2,Q3B577,B4SDA0,A1ANV0,Q4FNP9,A0T0H7,Q7N8Y4,Q6L0S7,A4SZR8,A1VMG2,B1XRU1,Q128K2,B2RJ90,P0C937,P69376,P69377,Q93GF1,B4S6P7,A2BZ91,B4F2V5,Q46I76,Q48E62,Q15UD3,A6VCL8,B7V1H3,Q02FR1,Q9HV43,B8H6Q1,Q1IF59,Q4KIH1,C3K275,Q3IC08,A4XYF6,A5W9A3,Q3KIA0,B0KIS5,Q88DU2,B1J254,Q9WWG9,Q87WP0,Q4ZNP7,A4VPQ5,Q4FPS9,Q1Q7X0,A1STE4,A5WI20,Q06W39,Q1XDH2,B2UBP3,Q8XW40,A9WQR3,B3PXH3,Q2KDW6,Q1MN11,O33528,Q98DD1,B5ZWQ2,P42374,Q7UM31,Q52701,B6IVA4,C0ZT86,Q21X09,Q9XCB1,Q2J320,Q07US6,Q6NCY4,Q21CI2,Q13E60,B3Q972,Q2RNE6,A3PNM1,Q3IYM7,A4WW89,O05700,C3PMM7,A8GMF9,Q1RHH0,Q92J36,Q4UJK7,Q9ZDX9,C4K110,B0BWH1,A8GR22,Q68XI2,Q16D45,Q1AXX6,Q5LWJ6,Q1GKS3,B8I305,A1AW22,Q21H36,B5F6Y8,A8LWM4,A9MR77,Q57TP3,B5FHA6,B5R5I2,B5RF08,B4TIB4,B4T6D6,Q5PDJ5,A9MXI2,C0Q4F3,B5BLH8,Q2S307,B4TVZ5,Q8Z9R1,A4X148,Q56073,A8G9K8,A1S8K7,B8E4S1,A3D7T4,A6WRU9,A9L0R8,Q12Q08,Q086J3,B0TQC2,A3QGW2,Q8EHT7,A8H760,A4Y9Q3,B8CKF3,A0KTS5,A8FYU0,Q0HLN0,Q0HY11,A1RGN1,B1KRT2,Q326K7,Q32KA5,Q0T8H6,Q83MH5,Q3Z601,A6UEY0,Q2NVZ1,Q01PM8,A5V5P9,A7X2Y1,A6U252,Q2FGE3,Q2FXZ2,A5ITA8,Q2YT47,Q5HFI0,A6QHC3,P64407,P99110,Q6GGC0,Q6G8Y7,A8Z4B9,P45554,P64408,B9DNK0,Q5HNW6,Q8CP17,Q4L6T0,Q49Y22,Q3K3T2,P0A3J2,P0A3J3,P0A3J4,Q05558,C0M7T9,A8AVA8,B1VMF3,Q54215,B4SSQ6,B2FMY5,O06942,P0C0C6,Q04LY0,P0DB70,B5E232,Q5XAD6,C1C5N7,P68837,Q1JA83,Q1JKD6,Q1JFC8,Q1J578,A2RCW6,B1IA52,B8ZLY9,Q48RR3,P95829,P0DB71,B2IMB5,P0C0C5,B5XHZ0,Q8CWT3,A4VZB5,C0ME86,A3CQC2,A4VT29,Q5M1T8,Q5M6D1,Q03MR6,B9DVF3,C1CCQ8,C1CJ06,C1CQ18,Q30Q10,A8Z5V5,A6QBG0,Q67S54,Q2LUH6,C5BQ33,Q93R27,A0T0X1,B7ID00,P50023,Q47TI0,A6LM32,Q9WYK6,B9KBT4,A5IK42,B0KA81,B0K3Y0,P96133,B1L9B4,Q72IK5,Q56235,Q97BG8,B5YH59,Q3SIN4,B8GNX1,C4L8Y5,Q73Q16,O83246,B2S2G4,P49463,O05714,P64410,P64409,B1H009,B1AIX8,Q9PQF2,B5ZBE9,C5CU12,A1WGJ9,A5CX56,A5F361,A7MWW0,O34241,C3LTA5,O87384,Q87RX3,Q9L7Z1,B7VJW9,Q8DF66,Q7MN85,Q8D2Q5,Q73GL7,B3CNB5,Q7MA35,Q5GSE1,C0R3W7,Q8PMB0,Q3BVB8,Q4UT11,B0RVU2,Q8PAK9,Q2P459,B2SQU4,Q5H186,A7IC65,B2I6F6,Q9PB05,B0U3J8,Q87BS8,A1JJD5,A7FME3,Q1C0J9,B2K3M0,Q8ZIM7,A9R015,Q1CMV7,A4TQF9,Q66ET0,B1JL04,Q5NPS6,P41753,Q00043,P78983,P48720,P16394,P27541,P91902,P08106,P25840,P26791,P40918,Q24789,Q5B2V1,O96772,Q95YL7,Q05945,Q07437,P27894,P17804,P14834,P11143,Q5UQ49,Q01233,P08108,Q91233,P11503,Q92260,Q05746,P11144,Q91291,P37899,P12795,P08418,P26413,O93866,P05456,P02827,P41797,P09189,Q02028">HSP70</z:uniprot> (24 h p.i., green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Nuclei were stained with DRAQ5 (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Bars, 10 µm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019860.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>puf2(-) sporozoites transform prematurely in the mosquito </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>In vivo data suggested that, over time, Puf2-knockout sporozoites rapidly loose infectivity in the mosquito ( Table 1 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>To better characterize this phenomenon, we carefully analyzed puf2(-) sporozoite development in the mosquito ( Figure 6 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Strikingly, we observed that a major proportion of puf2(-) sporozoites showed signs of premature transformation, characterized by a bulb-like aspect or even complete rounding-up ( Figure 6A ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>In WT parasites, transformation of sporozoites is typically observed at 37°C in culture medium, irrespective of the presence of host cells [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>In puf2(-)-infected mosquitoes, however, the proportion of transformed sporozoites increased over time during the course of infection in the mosquitoes, which are kept at 20°C ( Figure 6B ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Quantification of partial and complete transformation in all three parasite populations revealed that at day 29 almost all puf2(-) sporozoites had transformed, whereas only a minor fraction of WT and puf1(-) sporozoites exhibited signs of premature transformation ( Figure 6B ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, we did not observe expression of the liver stage marker UIS4 or nuclear divisions, as seen in EEFs (Figure 5C), in the transformed puf2(-) sporozoites ( Figure 6A ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019860-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019860.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Premature transformation of puf2(-) sporozoites in the mosquito. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>(A) Fluorescence microscopy of WT and puf2(-) sporozoites isolated from mosquito salivary glands 25 days after infection, and labelled with anti-UIS4 (red) and anti-<z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="28" ids="O33672,O33666,O33690,O33668,O33675,O33689,Q29455,Q9H3Z4,P60904,P60905,P56101,O42196">CSP</z:uniprot> (green) antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Nuclei were stained with DRAQ5 (blue). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Bars, 10 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>(B) The proportion of non-transformed, partially transformed and fully transformed sporozoites was determined by microscopic examination of sporozoites isolated from mosquito salivary glands 18, 21, 25 or 29 days after infection with WT, puf1(-) or puf2(-) parasites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019860.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>puf2(-) sporozoites have reduced levels of Puf1 and UIS1/IK2 mRNA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>The phenotype of puf2(-) parasites is essentially identical to that of parasites that contain a targeted deletion of the kinase UIS1/IK2 [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Similarly to puf2(-) parasites, ik2(-) sporozoites transform prematurely in the mosquito salivary glands and have a decreased infectivity in vivo but not in vitro [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we sought to test expression of IK2 in puf2(-) sporozoites, in comparison to WT and puf1(-) sporozoites, using RT-qPCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>As expected from gene deletion, no Puf1 and Puf2 mRNA were detected in puf1(-) and puf2(-) sporozoites, respectively ( Figure 7 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Whereas expression of UIS1/IK2 was not modified in puf1(-) sporozoites, we observed a ∼14 fold reduction of UIS1/IK2 mRNA in Puf2-deficient sporozoites as compared to WT ( Figure 7 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we found a ∼17 fold reduction of Puf1 transcript levels in puf2(-) parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Conversely, Puf2 transcript levels were not affected in the absence of Puf1 ( Figure 7 ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>As controls, UIS4 and <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="2" ids="A1TLH9,Q6F6N3,B7H317,B7IBK5,B2HZZ7,A3M8W9,B0V5U4,A0LWS7,C1F2D2,P81875,A5FZ19,B9MDJ7,B7J7X9,B5ENA3,P29133,A1WAR6,A3N3K0,B3H2X7,B0BTI7,A6VNB1,A0KMI6,A4SQ25,P71331,P50019,B9JZ87,B2UKV6,Q0VST6,B5FA11,A6TSM0,B4S0U1,B3ERN8,Q5PAB8,P86175,B7GKC8,O52960,O67118,O86103,A8EWT6,Q5P1H5,A0K1L3,A8IPT1,B6YRF7,A1K4C5,C3P8M0,C3L5R7,A0RIT3,Q81LS2,B7JN39,Q730M1,B7IYG7,C1ESK8,B7HCU0,B7HPL3,A7GT08,B9IY81,Q818E9,Q634M7,Q5LG30,Q64X01,Q9KD72,Q6HDK7,Q65H54,P05646,A9VHU1,A8FFD2,Q5WHG1,P17820,Q89YW6,A6L2X7,A7Z6W1,A1UUC3,Q6G554,Q6G1F9,A9ILH7,Q1LST3,Q6MNF8,B2IBR4,C5C3P2,B8DT62,A1A3P5,B3DNP9,Q8G6W1,B7GT47,Q7VQL4,Q493S7,Q2KWA2,Q0SMZ0,Q661A3,Q7WGI4,P0C922,B7J282,B5RM75,B2S0M0,Q7W519,A9IGC3,Q7VVY2,B5RPM1,P94317,C0ZB48,Q9LCQ5,Q57AD7,Q8YE76,Q05981,Q8FXX2,B8D8V4,O32464,Q8K9Y8,B8D758,P59565,B1YTK0,Q1BYX3,B1JW19,P42373,A0K4S8,B4EDZ2,Q0BI18,Q39JC8,A9AGB8,A3MN99,A2S565,Q62HD5,A1V0U6,A3NYX7,Q3JP10,A3ND68,O68191,Q2SYZ4,A4JBS1,B9MJZ1,Q8RB68,A4XKA4,A7ZEB5,A7GXU4,A0RPW7,A7I2D4,A8FLH2,A7H484,O69298,Q5HV33,B9KCH0,Q3AF08,Q05FS8,B0T138,P20442,B3PF33,A0RZ01,Q11KJ6,Q8GH79,Q3APD2,Q824B2,Q253K1,B3EHR1,P56836,B3QMB2,B3EKT9,A1BET8,A4SFB1,P27542,B0B7W6,B3QZ38,Q3KLV7,B0BC31,Q8KEP3,P17821,Q1QSX0,Q7NXI3,A8ALU3,A5CM86,B0RBI1,P30721,A7FXL5,C3L3G7,A6LRN4,B2V2I5,B2TLZ7,A5I640,C1FVU0,B1ILM3,A7GHH6,B1KZN7,Q182E8,B9E041,A5N6M2,A0Q1R4,Q0TNS7,P81341,P26823,Q0SRE3,Q892R0,C3PJM6,Q6NEY9,Q8FM78,A4QHJ0,Q8NLY6,Q4JXX6,C4LGV8,B1VHX4,B6J7U7,B6IZJ0,A9KG88,A9N8H2,O87712,A7MIK5,O33522,Q0K757,Q46XI7,B3R6G7,P0CY98,P0CY99,Q9TLT1,Q85FW4,Q37106,Q11QH3,Q47HK2,Q3Z6P1,A5FPU4,Q3ZYV1,C1CZH9,Q1IWL4,P94695,Q9RY23,P83709,A9BNG5,C6BSF2,Q313S2,C0QGP6,B8FGS3,B1I699,B8J402,B8FUN4,C4XQ63,A8ZRW3,Q6AMQ3,A4J7F3,Q72DW8,B8DRD6,A1VFG6,P30722,A5EYG3,B5YAR3,B8DYH6,A7ZHA4,P0A6Z0,A7ZVV7,A1A766,Q0TLX5,P0A6Y9,B1IRG0,P0A6Y8,Q1RGI8,C5B7L7,Q3YRR6,Q5FFM4,Q5HAY1,B2KAX0,Q4G366,A4W6D5,Q835R7,B2VGR9,Q05647,C4Z1J4,B1YKS9,C4L425,B0S1F8,A5FGL1,A6GXZ1,Q0RBC4,B0TYF2,Q14GW9,A7NCM9,Q2A328,B2SGV8,A0Q7F0,Q0BLK4,Q5NFG7,P48205,A4IX28,Q8RH05,B5EC42,B9M357,Q5KWZ7,B3E7W9,Q39PT7,Q45551,Q74H59,C6E643,C5D4U1,A4IR31,A5GDC8,Q7NDH1,A9HEA3,Q5FSL5,Q0BW82,A0M353,Q6B8V2,P29215,P48209,Q4QJW4,A5UBQ1,A5UF68,P43736,B8F7S6,Q0I3V2,Q2SMM8,A1WX31,B9LUC7,Q01100,Q9HHB9,B8CXL1,B0R3H4,Q9HRY2,Q18GZ4,C4K3I6,Q17VY4,Q7VIE3,B0TAD7,B6JPL0,B5Z9P0,Q1CV46,Q9ZMW4,B2URT8,P55994,A4G8D2,B0UWR4,A3DF25,Q31HA7,Q0BWZ9,Q5QXL1,A6T226,Q28VY3,A6WFV7,B5Y242,A6T4F4,B2GGP0,Q1IT15,Q84BU4,Q03QU1,B3WEQ7,Q1G9R2,Q049W6,B2GBQ5,Q044A9,A8YVQ3,Q74IT6,P0A3J0,P0A3J1,Q02ZQ7,Q038N3,A9KKU0,Q88VM0,A5VJE7,B2G6W3,Q1WUE8,O87777,Q8KML6,Q38W93,C1DD88,Q1MPW1,Q5X3M7,A5IDK8,Q5ZTY3,Q5WV15,O32482,Q6AC76,B0SHT1,Q04VC8,Q04Y47,B0SRF1,B1Y786,P61442,P61443,B1MZG6,Q03WI2,Q92BN8,G2K046,C1KVC0,Q71ZJ7,B8DE38,P0DJM2,A0AIS4,B1HUD1,O69268,B9E6X1,A0L4Z2,Q2VYT1,O52064,Q65U55,A1U614,Q0AKB1,A6W2D2,Q9ZIV1,Q6F149,Q8TQR2,Q0W874,Q465Y6,Q12WE6,B7KSZ4,Q607A5,A9W6R7,Q1H3B8,B3DZP7,P0CW13,P0CW12,B8IHL3,B1ZGR1,A2SIR4,B1LZ51,B0UR84,B8EIP9,Q9ZFC6,Q9UXR0,O27351,A0B747,Q2RKX4,A0QLZ6,B1MIX5,A5IXT5,P80462,P0A5C0,A1KFH2,C1AK26,Q2SSB0,Q7NAU6,P47547,A4T112,Q49539,Q4A8U5,Q4AAR4,Q9ZEJ0,B8ZTB7,P19993,B2HPS1,Q6KIH7,Q6MT06,Q00488,Q8EUH7,P75344,Q98QY7,A0QQC8,Q4A658,A3PTN4,A1UA31,P80692,Q1BEV1,A5TZ77,P9WMJ8,P9WMJ9,A0PLQ1,A1T2S3,P95334,Q3IUI0,B9L8Z0,Q5F6W5,A9M296,Q9JVQ9,Q9K0N4,A1KSG3,O85282,Q2GF34,Q0AIY1,O06430,Q1QRU1,A9A135,Q2Y6U0,Q3J7D8,A6Q421,Q3SW76,Q5YNI0,A1SPX5,Q2G6N0,Q8EPW4,Q04EE1,B6JCI3,Q6YPM1,A6LDG8,A1B4E9,A7HZ39,B2JGE2,B2SXC6,Q9KWS7,Q6MB26,Q145F1,P57870,Q6D0B7,C6DF10,Q03FR7,Q3A8C2,Q3B577,B4SDA0,A1ANV0,Q4FNP9,A0T0H7,Q7N8Y4,Q6L0S7,A4SZR8,A1VMG2,B1XRU1,Q128K2,B2RJ90,P0C937,P69376,P69377,Q93GF1,B4S6P7,A2BZ91,B4F2V5,Q46I76,Q48E62,Q15UD3,A6VCL8,B7V1H3,Q02FR1,Q9HV43,B8H6Q1,Q1IF59,Q4KIH1,C3K275,Q3IC08,A4XYF6,A5W9A3,Q3KIA0,B0KIS5,Q88DU2,B1J254,Q9WWG9,Q87WP0,Q4ZNP7,A4VPQ5,Q4FPS9,Q1Q7X0,A1STE4,A5WI20,Q06W39,Q1XDH2,B2UBP3,Q8XW40,A9WQR3,B3PXH3,Q2KDW6,Q1MN11,O33528,Q98DD1,B5ZWQ2,P42374,Q7UM31,Q52701,B6IVA4,C0ZT86,Q21X09,Q9XCB1,Q2J320,Q07US6,Q6NCY4,Q21CI2,Q13E60,B3Q972,Q2RNE6,A3PNM1,Q3IYM7,A4WW89,O05700,C3PMM7,A8GMF9,Q1RHH0,Q92J36,Q4UJK7,Q9ZDX9,C4K110,B0BWH1,A8GR22,Q68XI2,Q16D45,Q1AXX6,Q5LWJ6,Q1GKS3,B8I305,A1AW22,Q21H36,B5F6Y8,A8LWM4,A9MR77,Q57TP3,B5FHA6,B5R5I2,B5RF08,B4TIB4,B4T6D6,Q5PDJ5,A9MXI2,C0Q4F3,B5BLH8,Q2S307,B4TVZ5,Q8Z9R1,A4X148,Q56073,A8G9K8,A1S8K7,B8E4S1,A3D7T4,A6WRU9,A9L0R8,Q12Q08,Q086J3,B0TQC2,A3QGW2,Q8EHT7,A8H760,A4Y9Q3,B8CKF3,A0KTS5,A8FYU0,Q0HLN0,Q0HY11,A1RGN1,B1KRT2,Q326K7,Q32KA5,Q0T8H6,Q83MH5,Q3Z601,A6UEY0,Q2NVZ1,Q01PM8,A5V5P9,A7X2Y1,A6U252,Q2FGE3,Q2FXZ2,A5ITA8,Q2YT47,Q5HFI0,A6QHC3,P64407,P99110,Q6GGC0,Q6G8Y7,A8Z4B9,P45554,P64408,B9DNK0,Q5HNW6,Q8CP17,Q4L6T0,Q49Y22,Q3K3T2,P0A3J2,P0A3J3,P0A3J4,Q05558,C0M7T9,A8AVA8,B1VMF3,Q54215,B4SSQ6,B2FMY5,O06942,P0C0C6,Q04LY0,P0DB70,B5E232,Q5XAD6,C1C5N7,P68837,Q1JA83,Q1JKD6,Q1JFC8,Q1J578,A2RCW6,B1IA52,B8ZLY9,Q48RR3,P95829,P0DB71,B2IMB5,P0C0C5,B5XHZ0,Q8CWT3,A4VZB5,C0ME86,A3CQC2,A4VT29,Q5M1T8,Q5M6D1,Q03MR6,B9DVF3,C1CCQ8,C1CJ06,C1CQ18,Q30Q10,A8Z5V5,A6QBG0,Q67S54,Q2LUH6,C5BQ33,Q93R27,A0T0X1,B7ID00,P50023,Q47TI0,A6LM32,Q9WYK6,B9KBT4,A5IK42,B0KA81,B0K3Y0,P96133,B1L9B4,Q72IK5,Q56235,Q97BG8,B5YH59,Q3SIN4,B8GNX1,C4L8Y5,Q73Q16,O83246,B2S2G4,P49463,O05714,P64410,P64409,B1H009,B1AIX8,Q9PQF2,B5ZBE9,C5CU12,A1WGJ9,A5CX56,A5F361,A7MWW0,O34241,C3LTA5,O87384,Q87RX3,Q9L7Z1,B7VJW9,Q8DF66,Q7MN85,Q8D2Q5,Q73GL7,B3CNB5,Q7MA35,Q5GSE1,C0R3W7,Q8PMB0,Q3BVB8,Q4UT11,B0RVU2,Q8PAK9,Q2P459,B2SQU4,Q5H186,A7IC65,B2I6F6,Q9PB05,B0U3J8,Q87BS8,A1JJD5,A7FME3,Q1C0J9,B2K3M0,Q8ZIM7,A9R015,Q1CMV7,A4TQF9,Q66ET0,B1JL04,Q5NPS6,P41753,Q00043,P78983,P48720,P16394,P27541,P91902,P08106,P25840,P26791,P40918,Q24789,Q5B2V1,O96772,Q95YL7,Q05945,Q07437,P27894,P17804,P14834,P11143,Q5UQ49,Q01233,P08108,Q91233,P11503,Q92260,Q05746,P11144,Q91291,P37899,P12795,P08418,P26413,O93866,P05456,P02827,P41797,P09189,Q02028">HSP70</z:uniprot> mRNA levels were similar in the mutant and WT sporozoites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Altogether, these data indicate that Puf2 regulates a subset of genes in P. berghei sporozoites, including Puf1 and the kinase UIS1/IK2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The latter probably explains, at least in part, why the phenotype of puf2(-) sporozoites recapitulates that of IK2-knockout parasites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0019860-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019860.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>puf2(-) sporozoites have reduced levels of Puf1 and UIS1/IK2 mRNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Shown is an expression profiling by RT-qPCR analysis of Puf1, Puf2, UIS1/IK2, UIS4 and <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="2" ids="A1TLH9,Q6F6N3,B7H317,B7IBK5,B2HZZ7,A3M8W9,B0V5U4,A0LWS7,C1F2D2,P81875,A5FZ19,B9MDJ7,B7J7X9,B5ENA3,P29133,A1WAR6,A3N3K0,B3H2X7,B0BTI7,A6VNB1,A0KMI6,A4SQ25,P71331,P50019,B9JZ87,B2UKV6,Q0VST6,B5FA11,A6TSM0,B4S0U1,B3ERN8,Q5PAB8,P86175,B7GKC8,O52960,O67118,O86103,A8EWT6,Q5P1H5,A0K1L3,A8IPT1,B6YRF7,A1K4C5,C3P8M0,C3L5R7,A0RIT3,Q81LS2,B7JN39,Q730M1,B7IYG7,C1ESK8,B7HCU0,B7HPL3,A7GT08,B9IY81,Q818E9,Q634M7,Q5LG30,Q64X01,Q9KD72,Q6HDK7,Q65H54,P05646,A9VHU1,A8FFD2,Q5WHG1,P17820,Q89YW6,A6L2X7,A7Z6W1,A1UUC3,Q6G554,Q6G1F9,A9ILH7,Q1LST3,Q6MNF8,B2IBR4,C5C3P2,B8DT62,A1A3P5,B3DNP9,Q8G6W1,B7GT47,Q7VQL4,Q493S7,Q2KWA2,Q0SMZ0,Q661A3,Q7WGI4,P0C922,B7J282,B5RM75,B2S0M0,Q7W519,A9IGC3,Q7VVY2,B5RPM1,P94317,C0ZB48,Q9LCQ5,Q57AD7,Q8YE76,Q05981,Q8FXX2,B8D8V4,O32464,Q8K9Y8,B8D758,P59565,B1YTK0,Q1BYX3,B1JW19,P42373,A0K4S8,B4EDZ2,Q0BI18,Q39JC8,A9AGB8,A3MN99,A2S565,Q62HD5,A1V0U6,A3NYX7,Q3JP10,A3ND68,O68191,Q2SYZ4,A4JBS1,B9MJZ1,Q8RB68,A4XKA4,A7ZEB5,A7GXU4,A0RPW7,A7I2D4,A8FLH2,A7H484,O69298,Q5HV33,B9KCH0,Q3AF08,Q05FS8,B0T138,P20442,B3PF33,A0RZ01,Q11KJ6,Q8GH79,Q3APD2,Q824B2,Q253K1,B3EHR1,P56836,B3QMB2,B3EKT9,A1BET8,A4SFB1,P27542,B0B7W6,B3QZ38,Q3KLV7,B0BC31,Q8KEP3,P17821,Q1QSX0,Q7NXI3,A8ALU3,A5CM86,B0RBI1,P30721,A7FXL5,C3L3G7,A6LRN4,B2V2I5,B2TLZ7,A5I640,C1FVU0,B1ILM3,A7GHH6,B1KZN7,Q182E8,B9E041,A5N6M2,A0Q1R4,Q0TNS7,P81341,P26823,Q0SRE3,Q892R0,C3PJM6,Q6NEY9,Q8FM78,A4QHJ0,Q8NLY6,Q4JXX6,C4LGV8,B1VHX4,B6J7U7,B6IZJ0,A9KG88,A9N8H2,O87712,A7MIK5,O33522,Q0K757,Q46XI7,B3R6G7,P0CY98,P0CY99,Q9TLT1,Q85FW4,Q37106,Q11QH3,Q47HK2,Q3Z6P1,A5FPU4,Q3ZYV1,C1CZH9,Q1IWL4,P94695,Q9RY23,P83709,A9BNG5,C6BSF2,Q313S2,C0QGP6,B8FGS3,B1I699,B8J402,B8FUN4,C4XQ63,A8ZRW3,Q6AMQ3,A4J7F3,Q72DW8,B8DRD6,A1VFG6,P30722,A5EYG3,B5YAR3,B8DYH6,A7ZHA4,P0A6Z0,A7ZVV7,A1A766,Q0TLX5,P0A6Y9,B1IRG0,P0A6Y8,Q1RGI8,C5B7L7,Q3YRR6,Q5FFM4,Q5HAY1,B2KAX0,Q4G366,A4W6D5,Q835R7,B2VGR9,Q05647,C4Z1J4,B1YKS9,C4L425,B0S1F8,A5FGL1,A6GXZ1,Q0RBC4,B0TYF2,Q14GW9,A7NCM9,Q2A328,B2SGV8,A0Q7F0,Q0BLK4,Q5NFG7,P48205,A4IX28,Q8RH05,B5EC42,B9M357,Q5KWZ7,B3E7W9,Q39PT7,Q45551,Q74H59,C6E643,C5D4U1,A4IR31,A5GDC8,Q7NDH1,A9HEA3,Q5FSL5,Q0BW82,A0M353,Q6B8V2,P29215,P48209,Q4QJW4,A5UBQ1,A5UF68,P43736,B8F7S6,Q0I3V2,Q2SMM8,A1WX31,B9LUC7,Q01100,Q9HHB9,B8CXL1,B0R3H4,Q9HRY2,Q18GZ4,C4K3I6,Q17VY4,Q7VIE3,B0TAD7,B6JPL0,B5Z9P0,Q1CV46,Q9ZMW4,B2URT8,P55994,A4G8D2,B0UWR4,A3DF25,Q31HA7,Q0BWZ9,Q5QXL1,A6T226,Q28VY3,A6WFV7,B5Y242,A6T4F4,B2GGP0,Q1IT15,Q84BU4,Q03QU1,B3WEQ7,Q1G9R2,Q049W6,B2GBQ5,Q044A9,A8YVQ3,Q74IT6,P0A3J0,P0A3J1,Q02ZQ7,Q038N3,A9KKU0,Q88VM0,A5VJE7,B2G6W3,Q1WUE8,O87777,Q8KML6,Q38W93,C1DD88,Q1MPW1,Q5X3M7,A5IDK8,Q5ZTY3,Q5WV15,O32482,Q6AC76,B0SHT1,Q04VC8,Q04Y47,B0SRF1,B1Y786,P61442,P61443,B1MZG6,Q03WI2,Q92BN8,G2K046,C1KVC0,Q71ZJ7,B8DE38,P0DJM2,A0AIS4,B1HUD1,O69268,B9E6X1,A0L4Z2,Q2VYT1,O52064,Q65U55,A1U614,Q0AKB1,A6W2D2,Q9ZIV1,Q6F149,Q8TQR2,Q0W874,Q465Y6,Q12WE6,B7KSZ4,Q607A5,A9W6R7,Q1H3B8,B3DZP7,P0CW13,P0CW12,B8IHL3,B1ZGR1,A2SIR4,B1LZ51,B0UR84,B8EIP9,Q9ZFC6,Q9UXR0,O27351,A0B747,Q2RKX4,A0QLZ6,B1MIX5,A5IXT5,P80462,P0A5C0,A1KFH2,C1AK26,Q2SSB0,Q7NAU6,P47547,A4T112,Q49539,Q4A8U5,Q4AAR4,Q9ZEJ0,B8ZTB7,P19993,B2HPS1,Q6KIH7,Q6MT06,Q00488,Q8EUH7,P75344,Q98QY7,A0QQC8,Q4A658,A3PTN4,A1UA31,P80692,Q1BEV1,A5TZ77,P9WMJ8,P9WMJ9,A0PLQ1,A1T2S3,P95334,Q3IUI0,B9L8Z0,Q5F6W5,A9M296,Q9JVQ9,Q9K0N4,A1KSG3,O85282,Q2GF34,Q0AIY1,O06430,Q1QRU1,A9A135,Q2Y6U0,Q3J7D8,A6Q421,Q3SW76,Q5YNI0,A1SPX5,Q2G6N0,Q8EPW4,Q04EE1,B6JCI3,Q6YPM1,A6LDG8,A1B4E9,A7HZ39,B2JGE2,B2SXC6,Q9KWS7,Q6MB26,Q145F1,P57870,Q6D0B7,C6DF10,Q03FR7,Q3A8C2,Q3B577,B4SDA0,A1ANV0,Q4FNP9,A0T0H7,Q7N8Y4,Q6L0S7,A4SZR8,A1VMG2,B1XRU1,Q128K2,B2RJ90,P0C937,P69376,P69377,Q93GF1,B4S6P7,A2BZ91,B4F2V5,Q46I76,Q48E62,Q15UD3,A6VCL8,B7V1H3,Q02FR1,Q9HV43,B8H6Q1,Q1IF59,Q4KIH1,C3K275,Q3IC08,A4XYF6,A5W9A3,Q3KIA0,B0KIS5,Q88DU2,B1J254,Q9WWG9,Q87WP0,Q4ZNP7,A4VPQ5,Q4FPS9,Q1Q7X0,A1STE4,A5WI20,Q06W39,Q1XDH2,B2UBP3,Q8XW40,A9WQR3,B3PXH3,Q2KDW6,Q1MN11,O33528,Q98DD1,B5ZWQ2,P42374,Q7UM31,Q52701,B6IVA4,C0ZT86,Q21X09,Q9XCB1,Q2J320,Q07US6,Q6NCY4,Q21CI2,Q13E60,B3Q972,Q2RNE6,A3PNM1,Q3IYM7,A4WW89,O05700,C3PMM7,A8GMF9,Q1RHH0,Q92J36,Q4UJK7,Q9ZDX9,C4K110,B0BWH1,A8GR22,Q68XI2,Q16D45,Q1AXX6,Q5LWJ6,Q1GKS3,B8I305,A1AW22,Q21H36,B5F6Y8,A8LWM4,A9MR77,Q57TP3,B5FHA6,B5R5I2,B5RF08,B4TIB4,B4T6D6,Q5PDJ5,A9MXI2,C0Q4F3,B5BLH8,Q2S307,B4TVZ5,Q8Z9R1,A4X148,Q56073,A8G9K8,A1S8K7,B8E4S1,A3D7T4,A6WRU9,A9L0R8,Q12Q08,Q086J3,B0TQC2,A3QGW2,Q8EHT7,A8H760,A4Y9Q3,B8CKF3,A0KTS5,A8FYU0,Q0HLN0,Q0HY11,A1RGN1,B1KRT2,Q326K7,Q32KA5,Q0T8H6,Q83MH5,Q3Z601,A6UEY0,Q2NVZ1,Q01PM8,A5V5P9,A7X2Y1,A6U252,Q2FGE3,Q2FXZ2,A5ITA8,Q2YT47,Q5HFI0,A6QHC3,P64407,P99110,Q6GGC0,Q6G8Y7,A8Z4B9,P45554,P64408,B9DNK0,Q5HNW6,Q8CP17,Q4L6T0,Q49Y22,Q3K3T2,P0A3J2,P0A3J3,P0A3J4,Q05558,C0M7T9,A8AVA8,B1VMF3,Q54215,B4SSQ6,B2FMY5,O06942,P0C0C6,Q04LY0,P0DB70,B5E232,Q5XAD6,C1C5N7,P68837,Q1JA83,Q1JKD6,Q1JFC8,Q1J578,A2RCW6,B1IA52,B8ZLY9,Q48RR3,P95829,P0DB71,B2IMB5,P0C0C5,B5XHZ0,Q8CWT3,A4VZB5,C0ME86,A3CQC2,A4VT29,Q5M1T8,Q5M6D1,Q03MR6,B9DVF3,C1CCQ8,C1CJ06,C1CQ18,Q30Q10,A8Z5V5,A6QBG0,Q67S54,Q2LUH6,C5BQ33,Q93R27,A0T0X1,B7ID00,P50023,Q47TI0,A6LM32,Q9WYK6,B9KBT4,A5IK42,B0KA81,B0K3Y0,P96133,B1L9B4,Q72IK5,Q56235,Q97BG8,B5YH59,Q3SIN4,B8GNX1,C4L8Y5,Q73Q16,O83246,B2S2G4,P49463,O05714,P64410,P64409,B1H009,B1AIX8,Q9PQF2,B5ZBE9,C5CU12,A1WGJ9,A5CX56,A5F361,A7MWW0,O34241,C3LTA5,O87384,Q87RX3,Q9L7Z1,B7VJW9,Q8DF66,Q7MN85,Q8D2Q5,Q73GL7,B3CNB5,Q7MA35,Q5GSE1,C0R3W7,Q8PMB0,Q3BVB8,Q4UT11,B0RVU2,Q8PAK9,Q2P459,B2SQU4,Q5H186,A7IC65,B2I6F6,Q9PB05,B0U3J8,Q87BS8,A1JJD5,A7FME3,Q1C0J9,B2K3M0,Q8ZIM7,A9R015,Q1CMV7,A4TQF9,Q66ET0,B1JL04,Q5NPS6,P41753,Q00043,P78983,P48720,P16394,P27541,P91902,P08106,P25840,P26791,P40918,Q24789,Q5B2V1,O96772,Q95YL7,Q05945,Q07437,P27894,P17804,P14834,P11143,Q5UQ49,Q01233,P08108,Q91233,P11503,Q92260,Q05746,P11144,Q91291,P37899,P12795,P08418,P26413,O93866,P05456,P02827,P41797,P09189,Q02028">HSP70</z:uniprot> mRNA levels in WT, puf1(-) and puf2(-) P. berghei sporozoites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Expression data from three independent experiments are shown and were normalized to the level of <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="2" ids="P42212">GFP</z:uniprot> transcripts, which are expressed under the control of the <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P29521,P0CT31,P34824,P06805,P17506,P34823,P0CT32,Q40034,P14864,P14865,P28295,P84321,Q9YAV0,P40911,P84322,P19039,O29325,P02993,P41752,Q9Y713,Q00251,P41745,P54959,P29520,P53013,A8MAJ1,A0RUM4,Q96WZ1,P0CN31,P0CN30,P90519,Q92005,P41203,Q07051,Q8SS29,P31018,P14963,Q08046,P16018,B0R8C3,Q9HM89,Q18EY5,P84319,P84317,P84320,P84318,P84315,P84316,P51554,A2BN41,P34825,A8ABM5,Q41803,O49169,A6UV43,Q8TRC4,Q0W8G2,A7I656,Q464Z4,Q12WT3,Q2FRI3,Q57770,Q8TYP6,A2STF0,A4FWE9,A9A9U3,A6VGV6,Q8PUR8,A3CTG3,Q6LXI1,B8GIQ3,A5ULM5,A4YCR6,Q2NEL1,O27132,A0B7D6,P07810,A6UQ14,P81266,Q74MI6,Q3IUD8,Q01372,P27592,Q9YIC0,O64937,Q41011,A5DPE3,Q6L202,Q00080,Q01520,Q01765,P85915,P32186,Q9V0V7,O93729,A4WKK8,A3MV69,Q8U152,O59153,A1RRJ3,P26751,Q8LPC4,P27634,P35021,O42820,Q9HDF6,P17786,Q09069,P25698,Q26487,A3DMQ1,P25166,P17196,Q976B1,Q04634,P19486,P17197,C5A5P4,Q5JFZ4,B6YVG2,A1RXW9,C6A4R7,Q979T1,P43643,P86933,O24534,Q03033,O59949,P02994">EF1alpha</z:uniprot> promoter [26]. no amplif., no amplification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0019860.g007"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Plasmodium sporozoites must persist and remain infectious within the salivary glands of the mosquito for many days until they are eventually transmitted to a mammalian host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Inside the warm-blooded host they need to quickly leave the site of deposition in order to travel to the liver, invade hepatocytes and differentiate into liver stages [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>The transient developmental arrest of sporozoites inside mosquito salivary glands, termed latency [12], implies efficient control mechanisms to prevent premature transformation before transmission and during transmigration before reaching a suitable host cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>In this study, we identified a factor controlling sporozoite latency in P. berghei, the <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P09339,P70920,Q6NH63,Q8FTA8,Q8NQ98,Q4JVM4,Q937N8,Q9RTN7,P25516,Q2A1K3,O08451,A0QX20,O53166,Q9I3F5,Q1RKD5,Q92G90,Q4UK20,Q9ZCF4,Q68VV0,Q8ZP52,Q5HG69,P63433,P99148,Q6GH55,Q6G9K9,P63434,Q5HPJ0,Q8CPC2,Q59938,Q5SMF6,P36683,Q9ZL64,P56418,Q9I2V5,Q8ZRS8,P74582,P37032,P28890,Q85442,A4PBQ0,P13278,P31612,P82866,P56958">RNA-binding protein</z:uniprot> Puf2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>In the absence of Puf2, sporozoites transform prematurely in the mosquito, resulting in a severe loss of infectivity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Sporozoite conversion into liver stages requires initial remodelling of the parasite pellicle, with disassembly of the inner membrane complex (IMC) and appearance of a bulb that progressively enlarges until the initially elongated sporozoite has transformed into a round form [28], [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Previous work has shown that transformation of salivary gland sporozoites is induced at 37°C in culture medium, irrespective of the presence of host cells [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>It should be noted that differentiation into EEFs involves additional events, including expression of liver stage specific proteins, onset of nuclear divisions and parasite growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>None of these events are observed in axenic culture conditions [28], where instead extracellular sporozoites die rapidly after transformation [31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>We show that puf2(-) sporozoites transform prematurely in the mosquito salivary glands, as evidenced by the characteristic bulb-like structures and rounding-up of the parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Premature transformation probably impairs the sporozoite functions that depend on IMC integrity, such as parasite motility, cell traversal and invasion, thus resulting in a loss of infectivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>In the absence of Puf2, the proportion of transformed salivary gland sporozoites increases over time, which correlates with a progressive loss of infectivity to mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, although most puf2(-) sporozoites eventually transform into completely round forms, these forms do not progress to EEF differentiation, as shown by minimal expression of the liver stage marker UIS4 and absence of nuclear division or growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>In contrast, normal differentiation of puf2(-) parasites is observed once sporozoites invade cultured hepatoma cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Collectively, these data strongly suggest that Puf2 plays a major role in preventing premature remodelling of the sporozoites prior to liver infection, but is not required for EEF differentiation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>The defects observed in puf2(-) parasites are reminiscent of those described in IK2-knockout parasites [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Both puf2(-) and ik2(-) sporozoites transform prematurely in the mosquito and display greatly reduced infectivity to mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>However, both loss-of-function mutants are able to invade and differentiate into EEFs in cultured cells in vitro, indicating that they do not play any essential role after host cell infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>These observations, combined with a major down-regulation of IK2 expression in puf2(-) sporozoites, suggest that the phenotype of Puf2-deficient parasites can be explained, to a large extent, by IK2 depletion. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>How IK2 prevents sporozoite transformation has yet to be determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Phosphorylation of the alpha subunit of eIF2 by distinct kinases, such as Plasmodium IK2, is a central mechanism in stress-induced translational regulation [32], including in protozoans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>For example, the <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q9FE78">eIF2alpha</z:uniprot> kinase <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q13422,O15554,O89109,Q9QYW1">IK1</z:uniprot> regulates responses to starvation stress in P. falciparum blood stages [13], and in Toxoplasma gondii, phosphorylation of <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q9FE78">eIF2alpha</z:uniprot> promotes survival of extracellular tachyzoites [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Our data corroborate the findings of Zhang et al. [12], which together suggest that a similar stress response operates in sporozoites to maintain them in a quiescent stage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>The founding member of the Puf family, Drosophila melanogaster Pumilio (DmPUM), regulates, amongst other functions, abdominal development in the fly via translational repression of the maternally inherited hunchback (hb) mRNA [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>The Puf domain of DmPUM binds to a nanos response element (NRE) sequence located in the 3′ UTR of hb mRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Biochemical data, such as in vitro binding assays using recombinant Puf domains expressed in bacteria and heterologous in vivo studies using the yeast three-hybrid system, have demonstrated intrinsic binding activity of the P. falciparum PfPuf1 and PfPuf2 to the NRE sequence [20], [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Signature RNA sequences that are recognized by the Puf domain vary between species and members of the Puf family, but typically contain a UGUR motif [35], [36], [37], [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>A large number of Plasmodium genes contain UGUR motifs in their 3′ UTR, but their functional significance remains uncertain, especially in the context of the exceptional AT-richness of the Plasmodium genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Therefore, endogenous targets of Plasmodium Puf proteins still remain elusive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>The P. falciparum [22] and P. berghei (this study) mutants now constitute potential tools to identify Puf2 target genes in Plasmodium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>In sporozoites, Puf2 regulates at least two other genes in addition to IK2 and Puf1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Indeed, using RT-qPCR, we found a 4-fold reduction of Spect and Spect2 mRNA levels in puf2(-) sporozoites, whereas <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="72" ids="Q05214,P53491,P26182,P53455,Q75D00,Q2U7A3,O13419,P90689,Q92192,P14235,Q9UVZ8,P60009,P80709,P53498,P53499,O65315,Q9UVX4,P30161,O17320,Q92193,P48465,P26183,P53500,Q24733,Q8SWN8,P11426,Q8X119,P53502,Q39758,Q6TCF2,P51775,O81221,Q99023,P17128,Q9P4D1,P45520,P91754,O16808,O65316,P78711,O74258,Q39596,P53689,P13363,A5DQP9,P24902,P81085,P45521,P50138,P60011,O65314,P10989,Q11212,O00937,P68555,P10365,P53476,P53477,P20904,Q9UVF3,P60010">actin</z:uniprot> and <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P16445,P50492,P50489,P22621,P50490,P50491,P22622">AMA1</z:uniprot> were not affected (unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Reduced expression of Spect and Spect2 genes, which are both essential for sporozoite cell traversal and migration to the liver [29], [39], [40], may also contribute to the loss of infectivity of puf2(-) parasites in vivo. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Whereas Puf proteins typically modulate target mRNA expression by either promoting mRNA turnover or translational repression, they can also activate gene expression or control mRNA subcellular localization (reviewed in [18] and [19]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Our results are not compatible with a role of Puf2 in repressing IK2, because puf2(-) and ik2(-) share a similar phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Puf2 may instead participate in stabilization of IK2 transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, depletion of IK2 mRNA in puf2(-) could be an indirect effect due to activation of an upstream factor that regulates IK2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Whereas Drosophila encodes only DmPUM, many organisms, including C. elegans, contain two or more genes encoding Puf proteins, which can fulfil partly redundant functions [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Therefore, presence of two Puf genes in the Plasmodium genome might be explained by overlapping or distinct roles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>However, our molecular genetics data clearly exclude a vital role for Puf1 under normal conditions throughout the P. berghei life cycle. Puf1 may be critical under specific conditions, similarly to the role of <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q13422,O15554,O89109,Q9QYW1">IK1</z:uniprot> in P. falciparum during starvation-induced stress [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Puf2 might compensate for the absence of Puf1 in puf1(-) parasites, but not vice versa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>While Puf1 in principle might be able to functionally complement for Puf2 function, depletion of Puf1 at the mRNA level precludes a hypothetical functional overlap in vivo. In this regard, it should be noted that P. berghei Puf1 and Puf2 proteins are very different in size (1183 versus 477 amino acids, respectively), and share only little homology (∼27% identity) restricted to the Puf domains. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>P. falciparum parasites that lack Puf2 show increased gametocyte rates and a bias towards male gametocytes [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>These observations fit with the proposed unifying, and perhaps ancestral, role of Pufs in promoting cell proliferation and repressing differentiation [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Our findings that Puf2 inhibits sporozoite transformation further support the notion of a central role in suppression of cellular differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Because of the published data from P.falciparum puf2(-) parasites we did not investigate sexual development and differentiation of Pbpuf2(-) parasites in great detail other than to confirm the previous findings, i.e. an increase in gametocytogenesis in puf2(-) parasites, partly due to increased male gametocyte differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>In the previous study, life cycle progression of Pfpuf2(-) parasites beyond gametocytogenesis was not analyzed [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Based on our results in the rodent malaria model system, we predict that P. falciparum sporozoites lacking Puf2 will present a similar phenotype, that is premature sporozoite transformation in the mosquito and decreased infectivity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Therefore, our findings might be of considerable interest in the context of development of genetically attenuated parasites for vaccination [42]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we show here that Puf2 plays a major role in controlling sporozoite latency during host switch, possibly through the regulation of IK2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Our results also highlight the functional importance of post-transcriptional regulation of gene expression during transmission of the malaria parasite between hosts. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Ethics statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>All animal work was conducted in accordance with the German ‘Tierschutzgesetz in der Fassung vom 18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Mai 2006 (BGBl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>I S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>1207)', which implements the directive 86/609/EEC from the European Union and the European Convention for the protection of vertebrate animals used for experimental and other scientific purposes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The protocol was approved by the ethics committee of <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P69034,P19136">MPI</z:uniprot>-IB and the Berlin state authorities (LAGeSo Reg# G0469/09). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Experimental animals, parasites and cell lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Female NMRI and C57BL/6 mice were from Charles River Laboratories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>We used P. berghei ANKA clone 507 parasites, which constitutively express the <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P42212">green fluorescent protein</z:uniprot> (<z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="2" ids="P42212">GFP</z:uniprot>) [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>HepG2 cells (ATCC HB-8065) were cultured as described [43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>P. berghei Puf1 and Puf2 gene deletion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>A targeting construct for Puf1 gene knockout was generated by inserting a 503-bp 5′ fragment and a 575-<z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q64277">bp 3</z:uniprot>′ fragment on either side of a T. gondii <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="4" ids="P28019,P00376,P00378,Q07801,Q9U8B8,P00374,P04753,P00377,P09503,P27421,P22573,Q5HFZ7,P0A016,P99079,Q6GGY1,Q6G9D5,P0A017,Q8NWQ9,P0C0P0,Q5HPB1,P0C0P1,Q60034,A8AGY5,A7ZM66,P0AFS4,A8A0E8,A1ABF1,Q0THM2,Q8FHB1,B1IQY4,P0AFS3,B1LET0,Q1RBJ2,A4W9Z4,A6T8N3,Q320W2,Q32G72,Q0T4H1,Q83RC9,Q3Z1V9">DHFR</z:uniprot>/TS expression cassette. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>A construct for Puf2 gene knockout was generated by inserting a 1001-bp 5′ fragment and a 945-<z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="Q64277">bp 3</z:uniprot>′ fragment on either side of a human <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="4" ids="P28019,P00376,P00378,Q07801,Q9U8B8,P00374,P04753,P00377,P09503,P27421,P22573,Q5HFZ7,P0A016,P99079,Q6GGY1,Q6G9D5,P0A017,Q8NWQ9,P0C0P0,Q5HPB1,P0C0P1,Q60034,A8AGY5,A7ZM66,P0AFS4,A8A0E8,A1ABF1,Q0THM2,Q8FHB1,B1IQY4,P0AFS3,B1LET0,Q1RBJ2,A4W9Z4,A6T8N3,Q320W2,Q32G72,Q0T4H1,Q83RC9,Q3Z1V9">DHFR</z:uniprot> expression cassette. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Oligonucleotide sequences are indicated in Table S1. P. berghei parasites were transfected with linearized plasmids, using the Nucleofector® device (Amaxa GmbH) as described [44], injected intravenously into naïve NMRI mice, and selected by pyrimethamine treatment in the drinking water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Clonal parasite populations were obtained by limiting dilution series and intravenous injection of one parasite in 10 recipient NMRI mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>One puf1(-) and two puf2(-) clonal parasite lines were established and phenotypically characterized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Genotyping of WT and recombinant parasites was performed by PCR and Southern blot analysis of genomic DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Standard Southern blot analysis was performed using the PCR DIG Probe synthesis kit and the DIG Luminescent Detection kit (Roche), according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Real time quantitative RT-PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>Parasite total RNA was extracted with the RNeasy kit (Qiagen) and reverse transcribed with the RETROScript kit (Ambion). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Real time PCR was performed on cDNA preparations as described [11], using the StepOnePlus™ Real-Time PCR System and Power SYBR® Green PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems), according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Expression data were normalized using the constitutively expressed <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="2" ids="P42212">GFP</z:uniprot> gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Parasites were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) and permeabilized with 1% Triton X-100. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence was then carried out using previously described monoclonal antibodies against P. berghei <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="28" ids="O33672,O33666,O33690,O33668,O33675,O33689,Q29455,Q9H3Z4,P60904,P60905,P56101,O42196">CSP</z:uniprot> [45] and <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="2" ids="A1TLH9,Q6F6N3,B7H317,B7IBK5,B2HZZ7,A3M8W9,B0V5U4,A0LWS7,C1F2D2,P81875,A5FZ19,B9MDJ7,B7J7X9,B5ENA3,P29133,A1WAR6,A3N3K0,B3H2X7,B0BTI7,A6VNB1,A0KMI6,A4SQ25,P71331,P50019,B9JZ87,B2UKV6,Q0VST6,B5FA11,A6TSM0,B4S0U1,B3ERN8,Q5PAB8,P86175,B7GKC8,O52960,O67118,O86103,A8EWT6,Q5P1H5,A0K1L3,A8IPT1,B6YRF7,A1K4C5,C3P8M0,C3L5R7,A0RIT3,Q81LS2,B7JN39,Q730M1,B7IYG7,C1ESK8,B7HCU0,B7HPL3,A7GT08,B9IY81,Q818E9,Q634M7,Q5LG30,Q64X01,Q9KD72,Q6HDK7,Q65H54,P05646,A9VHU1,A8FFD2,Q5WHG1,P17820,Q89YW6,A6L2X7,A7Z6W1,A1UUC3,Q6G554,Q6G1F9,A9ILH7,Q1LST3,Q6MNF8,B2IBR4,C5C3P2,B8DT62,A1A3P5,B3DNP9,Q8G6W1,B7GT47,Q7VQL4,Q493S7,Q2KWA2,Q0SMZ0,Q661A3,Q7WGI4,P0C922,B7J282,B5RM75,B2S0M0,Q7W519,A9IGC3,Q7VVY2,B5RPM1,P94317,C0ZB48,Q9LCQ5,Q57AD7,Q8YE76,Q05981,Q8FXX2,B8D8V4,O32464,Q8K9Y8,B8D758,P59565,B1YTK0,Q1BYX3,B1JW19,P42373,A0K4S8,B4EDZ2,Q0BI18,Q39JC8,A9AGB8,A3MN99,A2S565,Q62HD5,A1V0U6,A3NYX7,Q3JP10,A3ND68,O68191,Q2SYZ4,A4JBS1,B9MJZ1,Q8RB68,A4XKA4,A7ZEB5,A7GXU4,A0RPW7,A7I2D4,A8FLH2,A7H484,O69298,Q5HV33,B9KCH0,Q3AF08,Q05FS8,B0T138,P20442,B3PF33,A0RZ01,Q11KJ6,Q8GH79,Q3APD2,Q824B2,Q253K1,B3EHR1,P56836,B3QMB2,B3EKT9,A1BET8,A4SFB1,P27542,B0B7W6,B3QZ38,Q3KLV7,B0BC31,Q8KEP3,P17821,Q1QSX0,Q7NXI3,A8ALU3,A5CM86,B0RBI1,P30721,A7FXL5,C3L3G7,A6LRN4,B2V2I5,B2TLZ7,A5I640,C1FVU0,B1ILM3,A7GHH6,B1KZN7,Q182E8,B9E041,A5N6M2,A0Q1R4,Q0TNS7,P81341,P26823,Q0SRE3,Q892R0,C3PJM6,Q6NEY9,Q8FM78,A4QHJ0,Q8NLY6,Q4JXX6,C4LGV8,B1VHX4,B6J7U7,B6IZJ0,A9KG88,A9N8H2,O87712,A7MIK5,O33522,Q0K757,Q46XI7,B3R6G7,P0CY98,P0CY99,Q9TLT1,Q85FW4,Q37106,Q11QH3,Q47HK2,Q3Z6P1,A5FPU4,Q3ZYV1,C1CZH9,Q1IWL4,P94695,Q9RY23,P83709,A9BNG5,C6BSF2,Q313S2,C0QGP6,B8FGS3,B1I699,B8J402,B8FUN4,C4XQ63,A8ZRW3,Q6AMQ3,A4J7F3,Q72DW8,B8DRD6,A1VFG6,P30722,A5EYG3,B5YAR3,B8DYH6,A7ZHA4,P0A6Z0,A7ZVV7,A1A766,Q0TLX5,P0A6Y9,B1IRG0,P0A6Y8,Q1RGI8,C5B7L7,Q3YRR6,Q5FFM4,Q5HAY1,B2KAX0,Q4G366,A4W6D5,Q835R7,B2VGR9,Q05647,C4Z1J4,B1YKS9,C4L425,B0S1F8,A5FGL1,A6GXZ1,Q0RBC4,B0TYF2,Q14GW9,A7NCM9,Q2A328,B2SGV8,A0Q7F0,Q0BLK4,Q5NFG7,P48205,A4IX28,Q8RH05,B5EC42,B9M357,Q5KWZ7,B3E7W9,Q39PT7,Q45551,Q74H59,C6E643,C5D4U1,A4IR31,A5GDC8,Q7NDH1,A9HEA3,Q5FSL5,Q0BW82,A0M353,Q6B8V2,P29215,P48209,Q4QJW4,A5UBQ1,A5UF68,P43736,B8F7S6,Q0I3V2,Q2SMM8,A1WX31,B9LUC7,Q01100,Q9HHB9,B8CXL1,B0R3H4,Q9HRY2,Q18GZ4,C4K3I6,Q17VY4,Q7VIE3,B0TAD7,B6JPL0,B5Z9P0,Q1CV46,Q9ZMW4,B2URT8,P55994,A4G8D2,B0UWR4,A3DF25,Q31HA7,Q0BWZ9,Q5QXL1,A6T226,Q28VY3,A6WFV7,B5Y242,A6T4F4,B2GGP0,Q1IT15,Q84BU4,Q03QU1,B3WEQ7,Q1G9R2,Q049W6,B2GBQ5,Q044A9,A8YVQ3,Q74IT6,P0A3J0,P0A3J1,Q02ZQ7,Q038N3,A9KKU0,Q88VM0,A5VJE7,B2G6W3,Q1WUE8,O87777,Q8KML6,Q38W93,C1DD88,Q1MPW1,Q5X3M7,A5IDK8,Q5ZTY3,Q5WV15,O32482,Q6AC76,B0SHT1,Q04VC8,Q04Y47,B0SRF1,B1Y786,P61442,P61443,B1MZG6,Q03WI2,Q92BN8,G2K046,C1KVC0,Q71ZJ7,B8DE38,P0DJM2,A0AIS4,B1HUD1,O69268,B9E6X1,A0L4Z2,Q2VYT1,O52064,Q65U55,A1U614,Q0AKB1,A6W2D2,Q9ZIV1,Q6F149,Q8TQR2,Q0W874,Q465Y6,Q12WE6,B7KSZ4,Q607A5,A9W6R7,Q1H3B8,B3DZP7,P0CW13,P0CW12,B8IHL3,B1ZGR1,A2SIR4,B1LZ51,B0UR84,B8EIP9,Q9ZFC6,Q9UXR0,O27351,A0B747,Q2RKX4,A0QLZ6,B1MIX5,A5IXT5,P80462,P0A5C0,A1KFH2,C1AK26,Q2SSB0,Q7NAU6,P47547,A4T112,Q49539,Q4A8U5,Q4AAR4,Q9ZEJ0,B8ZTB7,P19993,B2HPS1,Q6KIH7,Q6MT06,Q00488,Q8EUH7,P75344,Q98QY7,A0QQC8,Q4A658,A3PTN4,A1UA31,P80692,Q1BEV1,A5TZ77,P9WMJ8,P9WMJ9,A0PLQ1,A1T2S3,P95334,Q3IUI0,B9L8Z0,Q5F6W5,A9M296,Q9JVQ9,Q9K0N4,A1KSG3,O85282,Q2GF34,Q0AIY1,O06430,Q1QRU1,A9A135,Q2Y6U0,Q3J7D8,A6Q421,Q3SW76,Q5YNI0,A1SPX5,Q2G6N0,Q8EPW4,Q04EE1,B6JCI3,Q6YPM1,A6LDG8,A1B4E9,A7HZ39,B2JGE2,B2SXC6,Q9KWS7,Q6MB26,Q145F1,P57870,Q6D0B7,C6DF10,Q03FR7,Q3A8C2,Q3B577,B4SDA0,A1ANV0,Q4FNP9,A0T0H7,Q7N8Y4,Q6L0S7,A4SZR8,A1VMG2,B1XRU1,Q128K2,B2RJ90,P0C937,P69376,P69377,Q93GF1,B4S6P7,A2BZ91,B4F2V5,Q46I76,Q48E62,Q15UD3,A6VCL8,B7V1H3,Q02FR1,Q9HV43,B8H6Q1,Q1IF59,Q4KIH1,C3K275,Q3IC08,A4XYF6,A5W9A3,Q3KIA0,B0KIS5,Q88DU2,B1J254,Q9WWG9,Q87WP0,Q4ZNP7,A4VPQ5,Q4FPS9,Q1Q7X0,A1STE4,A5WI20,Q06W39,Q1XDH2,B2UBP3,Q8XW40,A9WQR3,B3PXH3,Q2KDW6,Q1MN11,O33528,Q98DD1,B5ZWQ2,P42374,Q7UM31,Q52701,B6IVA4,C0ZT86,Q21X09,Q9XCB1,Q2J320,Q07US6,Q6NCY4,Q21CI2,Q13E60,B3Q972,Q2RNE6,A3PNM1,Q3IYM7,A4WW89,O05700,C3PMM7,A8GMF9,Q1RHH0,Q92J36,Q4UJK7,Q9ZDX9,C4K110,B0BWH1,A8GR22,Q68XI2,Q16D45,Q1AXX6,Q5LWJ6,Q1GKS3,B8I305,A1AW22,Q21H36,B5F6Y8,A8LWM4,A9MR77,Q57TP3,B5FHA6,B5R5I2,B5RF08,B4TIB4,B4T6D6,Q5PDJ5,A9MXI2,C0Q4F3,B5BLH8,Q2S307,B4TVZ5,Q8Z9R1,A4X148,Q56073,A8G9K8,A1S8K7,B8E4S1,A3D7T4,A6WRU9,A9L0R8,Q12Q08,Q086J3,B0TQC2,A3QGW2,Q8EHT7,A8H760,A4Y9Q3,B8CKF3,A0KTS5,A8FYU0,Q0HLN0,Q0HY11,A1RGN1,B1KRT2,Q326K7,Q32KA5,Q0T8H6,Q83MH5,Q3Z601,A6UEY0,Q2NVZ1,Q01PM8,A5V5P9,A7X2Y1,A6U252,Q2FGE3,Q2FXZ2,A5ITA8,Q2YT47,Q5HFI0,A6QHC3,P64407,P99110,Q6GGC0,Q6G8Y7,A8Z4B9,P45554,P64408,B9DNK0,Q5HNW6,Q8CP17,Q4L6T0,Q49Y22,Q3K3T2,P0A3J2,P0A3J3,P0A3J4,Q05558,C0M7T9,A8AVA8,B1VMF3,Q54215,B4SSQ6,B2FMY5,O06942,P0C0C6,Q04LY0,P0DB70,B5E232,Q5XAD6,C1C5N7,P68837,Q1JA83,Q1JKD6,Q1JFC8,Q1J578,A2RCW6,B1IA52,B8ZLY9,Q48RR3,P95829,P0DB71,B2IMB5,P0C0C5,B5XHZ0,Q8CWT3,A4VZB5,C0ME86,A3CQC2,A4VT29,Q5M1T8,Q5M6D1,Q03MR6,B9DVF3,C1CCQ8,C1CJ06,C1CQ18,Q30Q10,A8Z5V5,A6QBG0,Q67S54,Q2LUH6,C5BQ33,Q93R27,A0T0X1,B7ID00,P50023,Q47TI0,A6LM32,Q9WYK6,B9KBT4,A5IK42,B0KA81,B0K3Y0,P96133,B1L9B4,Q72IK5,Q56235,Q97BG8,B5YH59,Q3SIN4,B8GNX1,C4L8Y5,Q73Q16,O83246,B2S2G4,P49463,O05714,P64410,P64409,B1H009,B1AIX8,Q9PQF2,B5ZBE9,C5CU12,A1WGJ9,A5CX56,A5F361,A7MWW0,O34241,C3LTA5,O87384,Q87RX3,Q9L7Z1,B7VJW9,Q8DF66,Q7MN85,Q8D2Q5,Q73GL7,B3CNB5,Q7MA35,Q5GSE1,C0R3W7,Q8PMB0,Q3BVB8,Q4UT11,B0RVU2,Q8PAK9,Q2P459,B2SQU4,Q5H186,A7IC65,B2I6F6,Q9PB05,B0U3J8,Q87BS8,A1JJD5,A7FME3,Q1C0J9,B2K3M0,Q8ZIM7,A9R015,Q1CMV7,A4TQF9,Q66ET0,B1JL04,Q5NPS6,P41753,Q00043,P78983,P48720,P16394,P27541,P91902,P08106,P25840,P26791,P40918,Q24789,Q5B2V1,O96772,Q95YL7,Q05945,Q07437,P27894,P17804,P14834,P11143,Q5UQ49,Q01233,P08108,Q91233,P11503,Q92260,Q05746,P11144,Q91291,P37899,P12795,P08418,P26413,O93866,P05456,P02827,P41797,P09189,Q02028">HSP70</z:uniprot> [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Polyclonal anti-UIS4 antibodies were raised in rabbits immunized with two synthetic peptides from P. berghei UIS4 (CLFTDEHKDEINDNIV and CNNVYNMENKSFGPYI) (Eurogentec). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>DRAQ5 (Biostatus) was used to stain nuclei. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Confocal pictures were obtained with a Leica TCS-SP microscope equipped with appropriate filters, and processed with Photoshop software (Adobe Inc.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Parasite growth and sexual development </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>C57BL/6 mice (n = 5) were injected intravenously with 107 infected erythrocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Four days later, the parasitemia was determined by microscopic examination of Giemsa-stained blood smears. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>To analyse exflagellation of male gametocytes, five microliters of tail blood were diluted 1∶25 in RPMI 1640 containing 10% FCS and 50 µM xanthurenic acid, and adjusted to pH 8.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>After 12 min incubation at room temperature, exflagellation centers were counted in a Neubauer chamber. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Mean parasitemia and gametocyte rates were compared using the Mann-Whitney non-parametric test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>After parasite transmission to Anopheles stephensi mosquitoes, the numbers of midgut oocysts and salivary gland sporozoites were determined at day 10–14 and day 18–25, respectively, and compared using the Kruskal-Wallis followed by Dunn's multiple comparison tests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Analysis of sporozoite in vivo infectivity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>C57BL/6 mice were injected intravenously with 1,000 WT or mutant sporozoites isolated from the salivary glands of infected mosquitoes, or exposed to 10 infected mosquito bites, as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Infection was then monitored daily by examination of Giemsa-stained blood smears. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>The delay of patency was defined as the time before detection of at least one erythrocytic stage in the smears. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>For quantification of parasite liver loads by real time RT-PCR, C57BL/6 mice were infected intravenously with 10,000 sporozoites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>At 42 hours post-infection, livers were harvested, total RNA was extracted with the RNeasy kit (Qiagen) and cDNA synthesized with the RETROScript kit (Ambion). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR was then performed with the StepOnePlus™ Real-Time PCR System and Power SYBR® Green PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems), using primers specific for P. berghei 18S rRNA and mouse <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="1" ids="P09124,P53429,O34425,P25858,Q0J8A4,Q7FAH2,Q6K5G8,P25861,P50321,Q01558,P26518,P26519,P26520,P26521,P10097,O96423,Q27890,P22512,P22513,P50322,Q9YFS9,Q9HFX1,P55071,O67161,O28542,Q757I2,Q12552,Q9HGY7,P24750,P34783,P15115,Q59199,P23722,Q00640,Q00301,P46795,P46796,P10096,P48812,P57384,Q07234,Q89AK1,Q92211,Q28259,P70685,P00356,Q9PJN6,Q9Z7T0,B0B879,P0CE13,P24748,Q00584,O52631,Q59309,P29497,Q1DTF9,P28844,Q8J1H3,P35143,O57479,P54117,Q01651,Q05025,P17244,P0CN75,P0CN74,P19089,Q9Y796,Q5XJ10,Q6BMK0,Q94469,Q01597,Q27652,P0A9B3,P20445,B7LQ20,P0C8Z1,Q9N2D5,P00362,Q4U3L0,P44304,Q5V061,B0R2M2,Q9HSS7,Q48335,Q9ZKT0,P55971,P00357,P04406,P87197,A2BLC6,P80534,Q59800,P24163,P24164,O32755,P55070,P52987,Q9UR38,Q92243,Q9N655,O57672,P51640,A6UUN9,A7IB57,P19314,Q12XM4,P10618,P19315,Q2FNA2,Q58546,P58839,A4FZL2,A9A6M9,A6VIW4,Q8PTD3,A3CYG8,Q6M0E6,A5ULT9,A4YHA5,Q2NEN0,O27090,A6URW1,P53430,P16858,A3FKF7,P94915,P64179,A0A0H3MAB5,P47543,P46713,P75358,A0QWW2,P9WN82,P9WN83,P83601,Q3IUT3,P54118,O59841,Q8TFJ2,O42259,O01360,P56649,Q8X1X3,Q5R2J2,Q01982,Q9P8C0,O13507,P26988,Q92263,Q6L125,P00355,Q9UW96,P32637,Q5RAB4,P27726,P24751,Q9V1P1,Q8ZWK7,A4WIW2,A3MTU1,P61879,O59494,A1RV79,B1YD06,P61880,P46406,P52694,P04797,Q8NK47,P29272,P39460,P0A1P1,P0A1P0,P32638,P20287,Q96US8,P24166,P24753,Q28554,I2BA89,P0DJO7,P0A9B5,Q8WZN0,Q4KYY3,P0A038,Q9Z518,Q59906,P0C0G7,P0DB18,Q5XDW3,P68777,P0DB19,P0C0G6,Q4J940,C3N6F0,C4KHW5,C3MQN0,C3MWN0,C3NGT6,C3NEV8,Q971K2,Q9HJ69,P00361,Q5JHB5,P17721,B6YUU0,C6A312,Q97BJ8,O83816,P09317,Q9UVC0,P51009,P51469,Q6CCU7,P08439,P09316">GAPDH</z:uniprot>, as described [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Liver parasite loads were compared using the Mann-Whitney non-parametric test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0019860.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>List of oligonucleotides used in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>(PDF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0019860.s001.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr. Georgina Montagna for critically reading the manuscript, Marion Hliscs for providing cDNA from P. berghei gametocytes and ookinetes, Dr. Taco Kooij for providing plasmids, and Dr. Sylvie Briquet for technical assistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by the Max Planck Society, and in part by grants from the European Commission (EviMalaR, #34), the Joachim Siebeneicher Foundation and the Chica and Heinz Schaller Foundation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>OS was a recipient of a Marie Curie Intra-European fellowship and an EMBO Long-Term Fellowship. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0019860-Amino1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>1 AminoRThibergeSMartinBCelliSShorteS 2006 Quantitative imaging of Plasmodium transmission from mosquito to mammal. <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="121" ids="Q9R053">Nat</z:uniprot> Med 12 220 224 16429144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Frevert1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>2 FrevertUEngelmannSZougbedeSStangeJNgB 2005 Intravital observation of Plasmodium berghei sporozoite infection of the liver. PLoS Biol 3 e192 15901208 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Silvie1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>3 SilvieOMotaMMMatuschewskiKPrudencioM 2008 Interactions of the malaria parasite and its mammalian host. Curr Opin Microbiol 11 352 359 18644249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Matuschewski1"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>4 MatuschewskiKRossJBrownSMKaiserKNussenzweigV 2002 Infectivity-associated changes in the transcriptional repertoire of the malaria parasite sporozoite stage. J Biol Chem 277 41948 41953 12177071 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Coleman1"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>5 ColemanBIDuraisinghMT 2008 Transcriptional control and gene silencing in Plasmodium falciparum. Cell Microbiol 10 1935 1946 18637022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Balaji1"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>6 BalajiSBabuMMIyerLMAravindL 2005 Discovery of the principal specific transcription factors of Apicomplexa and their implication for the evolution of the <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="A1A4R9,P05549,P34056,P58197,Q9N0N3">AP2</z:uniprot>-<z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="5" ids="P22877,P15435,P62904,P62905,P22886,P06723,P27078,P21442,P16407,P20709,Q38361,P25426,P22884,P36932,P27077,P04890,P08320,P06155,P37317,P03700,P20214">integrase</z:uniprot> DNA binding domains. Nucleic Acids Res 33 3994 4006 16040597 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-DeSilva1"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>7 De SilvaEKGehrkeAROlszewskiKLeonIChahalJS 2008 Specific DNA-binding by apicomplexan <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="A1A4R9,P05549,P34056,P58197,Q9N0N3">AP2 transcription factors</z:uniprot>. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 105 8393 8398 18541913 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Yuda1"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>8 YudaMIwanagaSShigenobuSKatoTKanekoI 2010 Transcription factor <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="A1A4R9,P05549,P34056,P58197,Q9N0N3">AP2</z:uniprot>-Sp and its target genes in malarial sporozoites. Mol Microbiol 75 854 863 20025671 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Yuda2"><text><SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>9 YudaMIwanagaSShigenobuSMairGRJanseCJ 2009 Identification of a transcription factor in the mosquito-invasive stage of malaria parasites. Mol Microbiol 71 1402 1414 19220746 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Aly1"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>10 AlyASMikolajczakSARiveraHSCamargoNJacobs-LorenaV 2008 Targeted deletion of <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P28324,P41158,Q9HD43,E9Q0N2,P98185">SAP1</z:uniprot> abolishes the expression of infectivity factors necessary for successful malaria parasite liver infection. Mol Microbiol 69 152 163 18466298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Silvie2"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>11 SilvieOGoetzKMatuschewskiK 2008 A sporozoite <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P04931,P32770,P86967,H2A0M0">asparagine-rich protein</z:uniprot> controls initiation of Plasmodium liver stage development. PLoS Pathog 4 e1000086 18551171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Zhang1"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>12 ZhangMFennellCRanford-CartwrightLSakthivelRGueirardP 2010 The Plasmodium eukaryotic initiation factor-2alpha kinase IK2 controls the latency of sporozoites in the mosquito salivary glands. J Exp Med 207 1465 1474 20584882 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Fennell1"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>13 FennellCBabbittSRussoIWilkesJRanford-CartwrightL 2009 PfeIK1, a eukaryotic initiation factor 2alpha kinase of the human malaria parasite Plasmodium falciparum, regulates stress-response to amino-acid starvation. Malar J 8 99 19435497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Braks1"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>14 BraksJAMairGRFranke-FayardBJanseCJWatersAP 2008 A conserved U-rich RNA region implicated in regulation of translation in Plasmodium female gametocytes. Nucleic Acids Res 36 1176 1186 18158300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Mair1"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>15 MairGRBraksJAGarverLSWiegantJCHallN 2006 Regulation of sexual development of Plasmodium by translational repression. Science 313 667 669 16888139 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Zamore1"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>16 ZamorePDWilliamsonJRLehmannR 1997 The Pumilio protein binds RNA through a conserved domain that defines a new class of <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P09339,P70920,Q6NH63,Q8FTA8,Q8NQ98,Q4JVM4,Q937N8,Q9RTN7,P25516,Q2A1K3,O08451,A0QX20,O53166,Q9I3F5,Q1RKD5,Q92G90,Q4UK20,Q9ZCF4,Q68VV0,Q8ZP52,Q5HG69,P63433,P99148,Q6GH55,Q6G9K9,P63434,Q5HPJ0,Q8CPC2,Q59938,Q5SMF6,P36683,Q9ZL64,P56418,Q9I2V5,Q8ZRS8,P74582,P37032,P28890,Q85442,A4PBQ0,P13278,P31612,P82866,P56958">RNA-binding proteins</z:uniprot>. Rna 3 1421 1433 9404893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Zhang2"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>17 ZhangBGallegosMPuotiADurkinEFieldsS 1997 A conserved <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P09339,P70920,Q6NH63,Q8FTA8,Q8NQ98,Q4JVM4,Q937N8,Q9RTN7,P25516,Q2A1K3,O08451,A0QX20,O53166,Q9I3F5,Q1RKD5,Q92G90,Q4UK20,Q9ZCF4,Q68VV0,Q8ZP52,Q5HG69,P63433,P99148,Q6GH55,Q6G9K9,P63434,Q5HPJ0,Q8CPC2,Q59938,Q5SMF6,P36683,Q9ZL64,P56418,Q9I2V5,Q8ZRS8,P74582,P37032,P28890,Q85442,A4PBQ0,P13278,P31612,P82866,P56958">RNA-binding protein</z:uniprot> that regulates sexual fates in the C. elegans hermaphrodite germ line. Nature 390 477 484 9393998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Wickens1"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>18 WickensMBernsteinDSKimbleJParkerR 2002 A PUF family portrait: 3'UTR regulation as a way of life. Trends Genet 18 150 157 11858839 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Quenault1"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>19 QuenaultTLithgowTTravenA 2010 PUF proteins: repression, activation and mRNA localization. Trends Cell Biol  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Cui1"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>20 CuiLFanQLiJ 2002 The malaria parasite Plasmodium falciparum encodes members of the Puf <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P09339,P70920,Q6NH63,Q8FTA8,Q8NQ98,Q4JVM4,Q937N8,Q9RTN7,P25516,Q2A1K3,O08451,A0QX20,O53166,Q9I3F5,Q1RKD5,Q92G90,Q4UK20,Q9ZCF4,Q68VV0,Q8ZP52,Q5HG69,P63433,P99148,Q6GH55,Q6G9K9,P63434,Q5HPJ0,Q8CPC2,Q59938,Q5SMF6,P36683,Q9ZL64,P56418,Q9I2V5,Q8ZRS8,P74582,P37032,P28890,Q85442,A4PBQ0,P13278,P31612,P82866,P56958">RNA-binding protein</z:uniprot> family with conserved RNA binding activity. Nucleic Acids Res 30 4607 4617 12409450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Fan1"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>21 FanQLiJKariukiMCuiL 2004 Characterization of PfPuf2, member of the Puf family <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P09339,P70920,Q6NH63,Q8FTA8,Q8NQ98,Q4JVM4,Q937N8,Q9RTN7,P25516,Q2A1K3,O08451,A0QX20,O53166,Q9I3F5,Q1RKD5,Q92G90,Q4UK20,Q9ZCF4,Q68VV0,Q8ZP52,Q5HG69,P63433,P99148,Q6GH55,Q6G9K9,P63434,Q5HPJ0,Q8CPC2,Q59938,Q5SMF6,P36683,Q9ZL64,P56418,Q9I2V5,Q8ZRS8,P74582,P37032,P28890,Q85442,A4PBQ0,P13278,P31612,P82866,P56958">RNA-binding proteins</z:uniprot> from the malaria parasite Plasmodium falciparum. DNA Cell Biol 23 753 760 15585133 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Miao1"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>22 MiaoJLiJFanQLiXLiX 2010 The Puf-family <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="P09339,P70920,Q6NH63,Q8FTA8,Q8NQ98,Q4JVM4,Q937N8,Q9RTN7,P25516,Q2A1K3,O08451,A0QX20,O53166,Q9I3F5,Q1RKD5,Q92G90,Q4UK20,Q9ZCF4,Q68VV0,Q8ZP52,Q5HG69,P63433,P99148,Q6GH55,Q6G9K9,P63434,Q5HPJ0,Q8CPC2,Q59938,Q5SMF6,P36683,Q9ZL64,P56418,Q9I2V5,Q8ZRS8,P74582,P37032,P28890,Q85442,A4PBQ0,P13278,P31612,P82866,P56958">RNA-binding protein</z:uniprot> PfPuf2 regulates sexual development and sex differentiation in the malaria parasite Plasmodium falciparum. J Cell Sci 123 1039 1049 20197405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-LeRoch1"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>23 Le RochKGZhouYBlairPLGraingerMMochJK 2003 Discovery of gene function by expression profiling of the malaria parasite life cycle. Science 301 1503 1508 12893887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Hall1"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>24 HallNKarrasMRaineJDCarltonJMKooijTW 2005 A comprehensive survey of the Plasmodium life cycle by genomic, transcriptomic, and proteomic analyses. Science 307 82 86 15637271 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Menard1"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>25 MenardRJanseC 1997 Gene targeting in malaria parasites. Methods 13 148 157 9405198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Janse1"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>26 JanseCJFranke-FayardBMairGRRamesarJThielC 2006 High efficiency transfection of Plasmodium berghei facilitates novel selection procedures. Mol Biochem Parasitol 145 60 70 16242190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Mueller1"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>27 MuellerAKCamargoNKaiserKAndorferCFrevertU 2005  Plasmodium liver stage developmental arrest by depletion of a protein at the parasite-host interface. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 102 3022 3027 15699336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Kaiser1"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>28 KaiserKCamargoNKappeSH 2003 Transformation of sporozoites into early exoerythrocytic malaria parasites does not require host cells. J Exp Med 197 1045 1050 12707302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Amino2"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>29 AminoRGiovanniniDThibergeSGueirardPBoissonB 2008 Host cell traversal is important for progression of the malaria parasite through the dermis to the liver. Cell Host Microbe 3 88 96 18312843 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Gantt1"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>30 GanttSMMyungJMBrionesMRLiWDCoreyEJ 1998 Proteasome inhibitors block development of Plasmodium <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="61" ids="D9TT09">spp</z:uniprot>. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 42 2731 2738 9756786 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Hegge1"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>31 HeggeSKudryashevMBarniolLFrischknechtF 2010 Key factors regulating Plasmodium berghei sporozoite survival and transformation revealed by an automated visual assay. Faseb J 24 5003 5012 20798246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Wek1"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>32 WekRCJiangHYAnthonyTG 2006 Coping with stress: eIF2 kinases and translational control. Biochem Soc Trans 34 7 11 16246168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Joyce1"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>33 JoyceBRQueenerSFWekRCSullivanWJJr 2010 Phosphorylation of eukaryotic initiation factor-2{alpha} promotes the extracellular survival of obligate intracellular parasite Toxoplasma gondii. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 107 17200 17205 20855600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Murata1"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>34 MurataYWhartonRP 1995 Binding of pumilio to maternal hunchback mRNA is required for posterior patterning in Drosophila embryos. Cell 80 747 756 7889568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Wang1"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>35 WangYOppermanLWickensMHallTM 2009 Structural basis for specific recognition of multiple mRNA targets by a PUF regulatory protein. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 106 20186 20191 19901328 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Wang2"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>36 WangXMcLachlanJZamorePDHallTM 2002 Modular recognition of RNA by a human pumilio-homology domain. Cell 110 501 512 12202039 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Gerber1"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>37 GerberAPLuschnigSKrasnowMABrownPOHerschlagD 2006 Genome-wide identification of mRNAs associated with the translational regulator PUMILIO in Drosophila melanogaster. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 103 4487 4492 16537387 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Koh1"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>38 KohYYOppermanLStumpfCMandanAKelesS 2009 A single C. elegans PUF protein binds RNA in multiple modes. Rna 15 1090 1099 19369425 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Ishino1"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>39 IshinoTChinzeiYYudaM 2005 A Plasmodium sporozoite protein with a membrane attack complex domain is required for breaching the liver sinusoidal cell layer prior to hepatocyte infection. Cell Microbiol 7 199 208 15659064 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Ishino2"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>40 IshinoTYanoKChinzeiYYudaM 2004 Cell-passage activity is required for the malarial parasite to cross the liver sinusoidal cell layer. PLoS Biol 2 E4 14737184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Lamont1"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>41 LamontLBCrittendenSLBernsteinDWickensMKimbleJ 2004 FBF-1 and FBF-2 regulate the size of the mitotic region in the C. elegans germline. Dev Cell 7 697 707 15525531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Hafalla1"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>42 HafallaJCSilvieOMatuschewskiK 2011 Cell biology and immunology of malaria. Immunol Rev 240 297 316 21349101 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Silvie3"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>43 SilvieOFranetichJFBoucheixCRubinsteinEMazierD 2007 Alternative invasion pathways for Plasmodium berghei sporozoites. Int J Parasitol 37 173 182 17112526 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Janse2"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>44 JanseCJRamesarJWatersAP 2006 High-efficiency transfection and drug selection of genetically transformed blood stages of the rodent malaria parasite Plasmodium berghei. <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="121" ids="Q9R053">Nat</z:uniprot> Protoc 1 346 356 17406255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Potocnjak1"><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>45 PotocnjakPYoshidaNNussenzweigRSNussenzweigV 1980 Monovalent fragments (Fab) of monoclonal antibodies to a sporozoite surface antigen (Pb44) protect mice against malarial infection. J Exp Med 151 1504 1513 6991628 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Tsuji1"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>46 TsujiMMatteiDNussenzweigRSEichingerDZavalaF 1994 Demonstration of <z:uniprot sup="inside" fb="0" ids="A1TLH9,Q6F6N3,B7H317,B7IBK5,B2HZZ7,A3M8W9,B0V5U4,A0LWS7,C1F2D2,P81875,A5FZ19,B9MDJ7,B7J7X9,B5ENA3,P29133,A1WAR6,A3N3K0,B3H2X7,B0BTI7,A6VNB1,A0KMI6,A4SQ25,P71331,P50019,B9JZ87,B2UKV6,Q0VST6,B5FA11,A6TSM0,B4S0U1,B3ERN8,Q5PAB8,P86175,B7GKC8,O52960,O67118,O86103,A8EWT6,Q5P1H5,A0K1L3,A8IPT1,B6YRF7,A1K4C5,C3P8M0,C3L5R7,A0RIT3,Q81LS2,B7JN39,Q730M1,B7IYG7,C1ESK8,B7HCU0,B7HPL3,A7GT08,B9IY81,Q818E9,Q634M7,Q5LG30,Q64X01,Q9KD72,Q6HDK7,Q65H54,P05646,A9VHU1,A8FFD2,Q5WHG1,P17820,Q89YW6,A6L2X7,A7Z6W1,A1UUC3,Q6G554,Q6G1F9,A9ILH7,Q1LST3,Q6MNF8,B2IBR4,C5C3P2,B8DT62,A1A3P5,B3DNP9,Q8G6W1,B7GT47,Q7VQL4,Q493S7,Q2KWA2,Q0SMZ0,Q661A3,Q7WGI4,P0C922,B7J282,B5RM75,B2S0M0,Q7W519,A9IGC3,Q7VVY2,B5RPM1,P94317,C0ZB48,Q9LCQ5,Q57AD7,Q8YE76,Q05981,Q8FXX2,B8D8V4,O32464,Q8K9Y8,B8D758,P59565,B1YTK0,Q1BYX3,B1JW19,P42373,A0K4S8,B4EDZ2,Q0BI18,Q39JC8,A9AGB8,A3MN99,A2S565,Q62HD5,A1V0U6,A3NYX7,Q3JP10,A3ND68,O68191,Q2SYZ4,A4JBS1,B9MJZ1,Q8RB68,A4XKA4,A7ZEB5,A7GXU4,A0RPW7,A7I2D4,A8FLH2,A7H484,O69298,Q5HV33,B9KCH0,Q3AF08,Q05FS8,B0T138,P20442,B3PF33,A0RZ01,Q11KJ6,Q8GH79,Q3APD2,Q824B2,Q253K1,B3EHR1,P56836,B3QMB2,B3EKT9,A1BET8,A4SFB1,P27542,B0B7W6,B3QZ38,Q3KLV7,B0BC31,Q8KEP3,P17821,Q1QSX0,Q7NXI3,A8ALU3,A5CM86,B0RBI1,P30721,A7FXL5,C3L3G7,A6LRN4,B2V2I5,B2TLZ7,A5I640,C1FVU0,B1ILM3,A7GHH6,B1KZN7,Q182E8,B9E041,A5N6M2,A0Q1R4,Q0TNS7,P81341,P26823,Q0SRE3,Q892R0,C3PJM6,Q6NEY9,Q8FM78,A4QHJ0,Q8NLY6,Q4JXX6,C4LGV8,B1VHX4,B6J7U7,B6IZJ0,A9KG88,A9N8H2,O87712,A7MIK5,O33522,Q0K757,Q46XI7,B3R6G7,P0CY98,P0CY99,Q9TLT1,Q85FW4,Q37106,Q11QH3,Q47HK2,Q3Z6P1,A5FPU4,Q3ZYV1,C1CZH9,Q1IWL4,P94695,Q9RY23,P83709,A9BNG5,C6BSF2,Q313S2,C0QGP6,B8FGS3,B1I699,B8J402,B8FUN4,C4XQ63,A8ZRW3,Q6AMQ3,A4J7F3,Q72DW8,B8DRD6,A1VFG6,P30722,A5EYG3,B5YAR3,B8DYH6,A7ZHA4,P0A6Z0,A7ZVV7,A1A766,Q0TLX5,P0A6Y9,B1IRG0,P0A6Y8,Q1RGI8,C5B7L7,Q3YRR6,Q5FFM4,Q5HAY1,B2KAX0,Q4G366,A4W6D5,Q835R7,B2VGR9,Q05647,C4Z1J4,B1YKS9,C4L425,B0S1F8,A5FGL1,A6GXZ1,Q0RBC4,B0TYF2,Q14GW9,A7NCM9,Q2A328,B2SGV8,A0Q7F0,Q0BLK4,Q5NFG7,P48205,A4IX28,Q8RH05,B5EC42,B9M357,Q5KWZ7,B3E7W9,Q39PT7,Q45551,Q74H59,C6E643,C5D4U1,A4IR31,A5GDC8,Q7NDH1,A9HEA3,Q5FSL5,Q0BW82,A0M353,Q6B8V2,P29215,P48209,Q4QJW4,A5UBQ1,A5UF68,P43736,B8F7S6,Q0I3V2,Q2SMM8,A1WX31,B9LUC7,Q01100,Q9HHB9,B8CXL1,B0R3H4,Q9HRY2,Q18GZ4,C4K3I6,Q17VY4,Q7VIE3,B0TAD7,B6JPL0,B5Z9P0,Q1CV46,Q9ZMW4,B2URT8,P55994,A4G8D2,B0UWR4,A3DF25,Q31HA7,Q0BWZ9,Q5QXL1,A6T226,Q28VY3,A6WFV7,B5Y242,A6T4F4,B2GGP0,Q1IT15,Q84BU4,Q03QU1,B3WEQ7,Q1G9R2,Q049W6,B2GBQ5,Q044A9,A8YVQ3,Q74IT6,P0A3J0,P0A3J1,Q02ZQ7,Q038N3,A9KKU0,Q88VM0,A5VJE7,B2G6W3,Q1WUE8,O87777,Q8KML6,Q38W93,C1DD88,Q1MPW1,Q5X3M7,A5IDK8,Q5ZTY3,Q5WV15,O32482,Q6AC76,B0SHT1,Q04VC8,Q04Y47,B0SRF1,B1Y786,P61442,P61443,B1MZG6,Q03WI2,Q92BN8,G2K046,C1KVC0,Q71ZJ7,B8DE38,P0DJM2,A0AIS4,B1HUD1,O69268,B9E6X1,A0L4Z2,Q2VYT1,O52064,Q65U55,A1U614,Q0AKB1,A6W2D2,Q9ZIV1,Q6F149,Q8TQR2,Q0W874,Q465Y6,Q12WE6,B7KSZ4,Q607A5,A9W6R7,Q1H3B8,B3DZP7,P0CW13,P0CW12,B8IHL3,B1ZGR1,A2SIR4,B1LZ51,B0UR84,B8EIP9,Q9ZFC6,Q9UXR0,O27351,A0B747,Q2RKX4,A0QLZ6,B1MIX5,A5IXT5,P80462,P0A5C0,A1KFH2,C1AK26,Q2SSB0,Q7NAU6,P47547,A4T112,Q49539,Q4A8U5,Q4AAR4,Q9ZEJ0,B8ZTB7,P19993,B2HPS1,Q6KIH7,Q6MT06,Q00488,Q8EUH7,P75344,Q98QY7,A0QQC8,Q4A658,A3PTN4,A1UA31,P80692,Q1BEV1,A5TZ77,P9WMJ8,P9WMJ9,A0PLQ1,A1T2S3,P95334,Q3IUI0,B9L8Z0,Q5F6W5,A9M296,Q9JVQ9,Q9K0N4,A1KSG3,O85282,Q2GF34,Q0AIY1,O06430,Q1QRU1,A9A135,Q2Y6U0,Q3J7D8,A6Q421,Q3SW76,Q5YNI0,A1SPX5,Q2G6N0,Q8EPW4,Q04EE1,B6JCI3,Q6YPM1,A6LDG8,A1B4E9,A7HZ39,B2JGE2,B2SXC6,Q9KWS7,Q6MB26,Q145F1,P57870,Q6D0B7,C6DF10,Q03FR7,Q3A8C2,Q3B577,B4SDA0,A1ANV0,Q4FNP9,A0T0H7,Q7N8Y4,Q6L0S7,A4SZR8,A1VMG2,B1XRU1,Q128K2,B2RJ90,P0C937,P69376,P69377,Q93GF1,B4S6P7,A2BZ91,B4F2V5,Q46I76,Q48E62,Q15UD3,A6VCL8,B7V1H3,Q02FR1,Q9HV43,B8H6Q1,Q1IF59,Q4KIH1,C3K275,Q3IC08,A4XYF6,A5W9A3,Q3KIA0,B0KIS5,Q88DU2,B1J254,Q9WWG9,Q87WP0,Q4ZNP7,A4VPQ5,Q4FPS9,Q1Q7X0,A1STE4,A5WI20,Q06W39,Q1XDH2,B2UBP3,Q8XW40,A9WQR3,B3PXH3,Q2KDW6,Q1MN11,O33528,Q98DD1,B5ZWQ2,P42374,Q7UM31,Q52701,B6IVA4,C0ZT86,Q21X09,Q9XCB1,Q2J320,Q07US6,Q6NCY4,Q21CI2,Q13E60,B3Q972,Q2RNE6,A3PNM1,Q3IYM7,A4WW89,O05700,C3PMM7,A8GMF9,Q1RHH0,Q92J36,Q4UJK7,Q9ZDX9,C4K110,B0BWH1,A8GR22,Q68XI2,Q16D45,Q1AXX6,Q5LWJ6,Q1GKS3,B8I305,A1AW22,Q21H36,B5F6Y8,A8LWM4,A9MR77,Q57TP3,B5FHA6,B5R5I2,B5RF08,B4TIB4,B4T6D6,Q5PDJ5,A9MXI2,C0Q4F3,B5BLH8,Q2S307,B4TVZ5,Q8Z9R1,A4X148,Q56073,A8G9K8,A1S8K7,B8E4S1,A3D7T4,A6WRU9,A9L0R8,Q12Q08,Q086J3,B0TQC2,A3QGW2,Q8EHT7,A8H760,A4Y9Q3,B8CKF3,A0KTS5,A8FYU0,Q0HLN0,Q0HY11,A1RGN1,B1KRT2,Q326K7,Q32KA5,Q0T8H6,Q83MH5,Q3Z601,A6UEY0,Q2NVZ1,Q01PM8,A5V5P9,A7X2Y1,A6U252,Q2FGE3,Q2FXZ2,A5ITA8,Q2YT47,Q5HFI0,A6QHC3,P64407,P99110,Q6GGC0,Q6G8Y7,A8Z4B9,P45554,P64408,B9DNK0,Q5HNW6,Q8CP17,Q4L6T0,Q49Y22,Q3K3T2,P0A3J2,P0A3J3,P0A3J4,Q05558,C0M7T9,A8AVA8,B1VMF3,Q54215,B4SSQ6,B2FMY5,O06942,P0C0C6,Q04LY0,P0DB70,B5E232,Q5XAD6,C1C5N7,P68837,Q1JA83,Q1JKD6,Q1JFC8,Q1J578,A2RCW6,B1IA52,B8ZLY9,Q48RR3,P95829,P0DB71,B2IMB5,P0C0C5,B5XHZ0,Q8CWT3,A4VZB5,C0ME86,A3CQC2,A4VT29,Q5M1T8,Q5M6D1,Q03MR6,B9DVF3,C1CCQ8,C1CJ06,C1CQ18,Q30Q10,A8Z5V5,A6QBG0,Q67S54,Q2LUH6,C5BQ33,Q93R27,A0T0X1,B7ID00,P50023,Q47TI0,A6LM32,Q9WYK6,B9KBT4,A5IK42,B0KA81,B0K3Y0,P96133,B1L9B4,Q72IK5,Q56235,Q97BG8,B5YH59,Q3SIN4,B8GNX1,C4L8Y5,Q73Q16,O83246,B2S2G4,P49463,O05714,P64410,P64409,B1H009,B1AIX8,Q9PQF2,B5ZBE9,C5CU12,A1WGJ9,A5CX56,A5F361,A7MWW0,O34241,C3LTA5,O87384,Q87RX3,Q9L7Z1,B7VJW9,Q8DF66,Q7MN85,Q8D2Q5,Q73GL7,B3CNB5,Q7MA35,Q5GSE1,C0R3W7,Q8PMB0,Q3BVB8,Q4UT11,B0RVU2,Q8PAK9,Q2P459,B2SQU4,Q5H186,A7IC65,B2I6F6,Q9PB05,B0U3J8,Q87BS8,A1JJD5,A7FME3,Q1C0J9,B2K3M0,Q8ZIM7,A9R015,Q1CMV7,A4TQF9,Q66ET0,B1JL04,Q5NPS6,P91902">heat-shock protein 70</z:uniprot> in the sporozoite stage of malaria parasites. Parasitol Res 80 16 21 8153120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0019860-Putrianti1"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>47 PutriantiEDSilvieOKordesMBorrmannSMatuschewskiK 2009 Vaccine-like immunity against malaria by repeated causal-prophylactic treatment of liver-stage Plasmodium parasites. J Infect Dis 199 899 903 19434915 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
